<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bellum grammaticale a discourse of great warand dissention betwene two worthy princes, the noune and the uerbe, contending for the chefe place or dignitie in oration : very pleasant &amp; profitable / turned into English by W.H.</title>
            <author>Guarna, Andrea.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1569</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02288</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12419</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2699</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24514793</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24514793</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02288)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1852:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bellum grammaticale a discourse of great warand dissention betwene two worthy princes, the noune and the uerbe, contending for the chefe place or dignitie in oration : very pleasant &amp; profitable / turned into English by W.H.</title>
                  <author>Guarna, Andrea.</author>
                  <author>Hayward, William, fl. 1570-1576.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[95] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henrie Bynneman, dwelling in Knightrider strete, at the signe of the Mermayde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1569.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"First made in Latin by the learned Lord Andrew Guarna of        Salerne, and after translated into French, and now ... turned into English"--P. [15].</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: William Haywarde.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁸.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound and slightly faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Latin language --  Grammar --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27750:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27750:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellum Grammaticale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ A diſcourſe of great war and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention <hi>betwene two wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> Princes, the Noune and <hi>the Verbe, contending</hi> for the chefe place or dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in Oration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Very pleaſant &amp; profitable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Turned into engliſh by W. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IMPRINTED AT LONDON by Henrie Bynneman, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Knightrider ſtrete, at the ſigne of the Mermayde.</p>
            <p>ANNO 1569.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:27750:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27750:2"/>
            <lg>
               <head>GASPAR AVIATVS Cremonenſis.</head>
               <l>LEctor candide, quid legis Thyesten?</l>
               <l>Saeuas Colchidas? auribus placebunt</l>
               <l>Quae doctus cecinit magis Salernus</l>
               <l>Andreas: dubios mouet tumultus</l>
               <l>Verbi &amp; Nominis, hinc &amp; hinc furentum:</l>
               <l>Hunc (Lector) lege, fabulae faceſsant:</l>
               <l>Hic prompti Ciceronis est facultas:</l>
               <l>Hic ſunt ridiculi ſales, ioci<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>:</l>
               <l>Quid ſtas? hunc rigidi legunt Catones.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>HIERONYMVS FONDVLVS etiam Cremonenſis.</head>
               <l>Nominis et verbi Lector) ſtipe ſumito bellu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
               <l>Quo pax nulla quidem dulcior eſse potest.</l>
               <l>Bella recognoſces, quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſine partibus, hoc est</l>
               <l>Eloquia, omnis homo cederet vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> feris.</l>
               <l>Hic iocus Andreae defluxit ab ore Salerni,</l>
               <l>Fluxerunt lepidi cum grauitate ſales.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IDEM.</head>
               <l>Ranaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et muru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bellè haud ponit Homerꝰ,</l>
               <l>Bella gigantaeas non ita Naſo manus,</l>
               <l>Andraeas quanta cum maiestate Salernus</l>
               <l>Ingenij, Bellum Grammaticale canit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>CHRISTOPHORVS Simonetus.</head>
               <l>Haec legat, &amp; memori teneat certamina me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Grammaticus, terſo qui volet ore loqui.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:27750:3"/>
            <head>Ad Lectorem.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Diſce Puer, quando tempus permittit, &amp; ipſa</l>
               <l>Rectè diſcendi cauſa parata datur.</l>
               <l>Ordine tunc tua res poterit procedere recto,</l>
               <l>Si bene cunctorum ſingula facta notes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Adſis ergo (Lector) ſi ſit tibicura Latini</l>
               <l>Fac properes dulceis imbibiturus aquas:</l>
               <l>Aurea fluctifero ſunt merſa monilia ponto,</l>
               <l>Virtus ast nunquam mergier vlla potest.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:27750:3"/>
            <head>Lectori.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SYth Time permits, refuſe not, nor diſdayne</l>
               <l>to learne a right ſuch things as here be founde:</l>
               <l>For why? this Author firſt herein did take the paine,</l>
               <l>hereby to ſhewe of Grammer rules the ground.</l>
               <l>In order good thy workes will then appeare,</l>
               <l>and from right rule not ſeeme to ſwarue a iote.</l>
               <l>If all the actes of theſe archieued here</l>
               <l>accordingly thou well thou do weigh and note.</l>
               <l>Come nigh therfore (I ſay) and take a taſte</l>
               <l>of pleaſant liquours here detected plaine,</l>
               <l>If that thou couet ſpeedily in haſte,</l>
               <l>of Latine ſtile to chooſe the fruitefull graine:</l>
               <l>For all things fade, as brouches, golde and ſtone,</l>
               <l>when vertue ſwimmes, and ſcapes to ſhore alone.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27750:4"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull Maſter Thomas Povvle eſquier, Clerke of <hi>the Crowne in the Queenes Maieſties <hi>honourable Courte of Chauncerie, and one</hi> of the Six Clerkes of the ſame,</hi> William Hayward wiſheth health, with long life and proſperitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Seneca</hi> ſhamed not to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cite the worthy ſaying of the Poete <hi>Heſiodus,</hi> ſo I doubt not, but I may alſo (from ſo ſuſſcient authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as by <hi>Seneca</hi> him ſelfe in a certaine Epiſtle by him alleaged) partly ſeeme to ouerthrowe that moſt horrible monſter Ingratitude, and thoroughly to diſplace ſo vnnaturall affection before he ſhall by entertainment in ſo ſimple an one as I, (not able to be thankful) cauſe any part of obliuion for the benefites that haue bene towards me in any part extended: For (as I remember) he ſayth: <hi>Nullum efficium magis quàm referenda gratia, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium,</hi> that no duetie is more neceſſary
<pb facs="tcp:27750:4"/>
than re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred thanks to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred ſuch ample benefits as ſome haue beſtowed: and to render thankes (ſayth he) with greater meſure than they vſed to receyue commodities. For as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth <hi>Lib. 1. de officijs,</hi> If rendred thanks be due to ſuche of whome we hope to be benefited, howe muche more then is due to thoſe by whom we haue had already profit? Which albeit that I of my ſelf in euery point am moſte vnable to do, yet good will of ouermeaſuring (if poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie were in me) ſhall not ſeeme vtterly to be abſent, neither thinking that I can or am able to make any ſhewe of remu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and for that my inſufficiencie is ſuch as it is, it might ſeme on my part but preſumption to attribute any ſuche worthineſſe vnto him, that is altogether voyde of deſiring any ſuch preeminence. Yet among diuerſe and ſundry practiſes that by my poore induſtrie I haue atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, conſideryng that commoditie and frendly aide that your worſhip hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by your laborous trauaile toward that company, of which I am a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber:
<pb facs="tcp:27750:5"/>
and then waying my greate vnabilitie to requite in any way the leaſt parte of your manyfold curteſies, I was diſmay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to repreſent in this place any part of them, leaſt I ſhould ſéeme of the wiſe too gréede of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation. But being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened with your fauourable beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and accuſtomed courteous lenitie imployed towards al men: and making bolde of your woonted good will, that is, (and euer hath bene) ready to accepte a ſimple thing proffered and fréely giuen, rather than to reiect &amp; caſt off that which is meerely grounded of poore ſimplicitie, after I had peruſed the rable of my poore labours, founde among them this one, which then I was encoraged to dedicate vnto your gentleneſſe, not for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe therof as concerning my labor, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering your worſhips minde of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes with ſerious matters to bée encombred both in carefulneſſe toward the weale publike according to your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, as alſo for the benefits of ſuch poore men as I. Some thing therefore after your earneſt buſineſſe, to reuiue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create
<pb facs="tcp:27750:5"/>
your wearied minde with honeſt lerned and profitable mirth, I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to offer this my little labour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your learned eares, it being the firſt fruites of an vnproined orcharde, in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng wherof, notwithſtanding the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauerie ſappe of ſundry water boughes) may appeare both learned and fruitfull matter. And therfore I chiefly tooke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to tranſlate the ſame oute of the french tong, as earſt it was, for the like pleaſure and pithineſſe cauſe turned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of Latin into French, in which tong it was firſt (by a righte learned and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous man) written and inuented. In which deuiſe is contained a moſt perfect ſhew of horrible and bitter contentions in the moſt fertile region and countrey of <hi>Grammer,</hi> by variance that grew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixte two high and mightie Princes, poſſeſſors of the ſame, the <hi>Noune</hi> and the <hi>Verbe. <hi>Nomen,</hi>
               </hi> with his Subſtantiues, and Adiectiues, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons and Propers: with alſo the nobles of the houſe of maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culines, with the worthineſſe of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogie of Feminines, Neutres, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulles,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:6"/>
and Epicines, the Heteroclites, with their noble Capitaines, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, the Defectiues, and Redundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, with his moſte mighty brother the <hi>Pronoune,</hi> and his ſworne ſtoute warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors the Gentiles. Agayne <hi>Verbum</hi> with his nobles, with the Participles, Modes and Tenſes, with Gerundes &amp; Supins, in the great fielde of Coniunctions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending where they met for ſuperiority in gouernement. Wherin although but ſpoke <hi>Allegoricè,</hi> or rather written by the figure <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> ſheweth in part the troubles of a fained Common weale by inteſtine and Ciuile contention ſprong vp in the ſame. With ſuch pleaſant <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſis</hi> and arde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Allegories the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Poets vſed to beautifie their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, as <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> who vſed ſuche co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert fable againſt <hi>Philip,</hi> that required ten of the <hi>Athenienſes</hi> Oratours) ſaying how the Wolfe perſuaded and beſought the Shephierdes to tie vp their Doggs, and ſo to ioyned with them in friendſhip. Which when the Shephierds had grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Wolfe then as it were with a
<pb facs="tcp:27750:6"/>
couered &amp; licenſed crafty crueltie ſpoiled their flocks. So wrote <hi>Eſope, Horace,</hi> &amp; diuers other, which although but in part as Fables, (as this after a ſort is) is yet in ſome reſpect duly to be noted, as <hi>Saint Ambroſe</hi> affirmeth, ſaying: <hi>Ei ſi fabula vim veritatis non habeat, tamenratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, vt iuxta eam veritas manifestari poſsit:</hi> that is: Allthough a fable haue not the ſtrength of the truth, yet hath it a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that by it the truth may be vttered. Such was the maner of philoſophers, as <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> ſayth, to allure mens min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to the vnderſtanding of the trueth, which thing now as it is but fained, yet knowyng it to be deuiſed of ſo learned a man at the firſt, thought with my ſelfe, that thoſe whiche had capacitie mighte reape ſome fruite of his trauellous toy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. And agayne, ſuppoſing that if the ſame wer engliſhed, ſome might the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlier gather the ſenſe of the firſt author. Therfore as the Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlater therof out of Latine did for the recreation of a noble perſonage labor in the ſame, ſo I for the pleaſant profite of ſundry of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb facs="tcp:27750:7"/>
men, ſo duely as I coulde after my preſident, turned it into Engliſhe. And therfore as firſt and chiefeſt (it being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the firſt of my labours) I exhibite it to youre worſhip, not as a gifte (for any part of my deſeruing) worthie to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued: but by way of duetie offered, of mere good will, making you the patron of this my firſt enterpriſed atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt: choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing rather to ſuffer the reproche of the wiſe and the curious carping checke of <hi>Momus</hi> and his mates, with the perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious taunt of priuie paraſites, than to ſéeme altogether obliuious of my dutie, and ſo be accompted ingratefull. Which poore and ſlender thing if it pleaſe your worſhip to receyue wyth a friendly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect at my ſimple handes: your fauora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble encouragement ſhall hereafter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure me to finiſhe ſome greater effect to the benefite of my Countreymen (I meane ſuch as are deſirous to employe their labour in reading:) And in eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to manifeſt Gods doing in me, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the meane ſeaſon I beſéech to conduct and guide youre goodneſſe forth in that
<pb facs="tcp:27750:7"/>
well doing that he hath alreadie begon in you (in the ſuppreſſion of godleſſe ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, the very nourice of noughtineſſe: the ſufferance of which are the decay of Common wealthes, the corruption of youth, the breach of brotherhead and all true dealyng.) I ceaſſe to ſpeake of ſuch ſingularitie as all men ſhall ſée enſue of your dayly endeuours, and of that due commendation that may be ſayd of your Princely practiſe, that maynteyner of honeſt exerciſe: whereof right worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly your worſhip is maiſter, being a moſt perfect preſident in that practiſe (I mean of that laudable auncient and noble ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Shooting in the Long bowe) for euery one to folowe in effect. The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary vſe wherof, howe néedefull it is to be looked to, howe beneficiall the vſe thereof hath bene to this our countrey, how daungerous the neglecting thereof is, and howe hurtfull the lacke of vſyng the ſame of our youth in <hi>Englande</hi> hath bene, is too apparaunt. The almightie eaſe vs, whome I beſéeche ſo to endue you with preſent conſolation hoped for
<pb facs="tcp:27750:8"/>
in Chriſte, in thys lyfe your dayes may be long: And that after this lyfe, youre lotte (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayeth) may fal in a good grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that is, in Lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worships dayly welwisher. <hi>William Haywarde.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:27750:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Preface vpon the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoricall diſcourſe of the Grammer warre,</hi> firſt made in Latin by the learned Lord <hi>Andrew Guarna of Salerne, and after</hi> tranſlated into Frenche, and now for the worthineſſe of the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie turned into Engliſh.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt and auncient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers that wrote their Poeſies couertly hidden vnder ſubtile and wily matter, dydde conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute <hi>Pallas</hi> the daughter of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> borne in hir Soueraigne heade to be goddeſſe of wiſedome ſayd <hi>Minerue,</hi> and of warre, called <hi>Enyo</hi> or <hi>Bellona.</hi> Gyuing hereby to vnderſtande that of one and the ſame beginning, in one time altogether and in one ſubſtance are two principall things inſeparately ioyned together: whiche two properties are ſo knitte, that the one wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other is of no force, and the other without his fellow, of ſmal or no accompt: Yea, they are the principles whereby men attayne to the top of honoure, and famous felicitie, aduauncing meane men to honor
<pb facs="tcp:27750:9"/>
in their life time, and immortall fame after death. They are learnyng and martial pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſſe. Of theſe two together Noble Grece made ſeparation in his two metropolitanes when the Citie of Athens florished in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and the citie of Sparta or Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia glorious in feates of armes. The noble fame of the Romains grew by the one, and by the other they did alwayes defend them, ſo that they dyd ſucceſsiuely greately ſette ſtore by them. The worthie, valiaunt, and myghtie Eloquent <hi>Caeſar</hi> was decored with them bothe, and by them dyd eterniſe hys Renoune. Beholde (gentle Reader) nowe theſe two ſo worthie things, whiche are no leſſe principals to the gouernement of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, Realmes, Reipublikes, and for all eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates of the world to be aptely vnderſtode, which did ſo much ennoble Grece, ſo gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour the Romaines, and eterniſe the fame of the great <hi>Caeſar,</hi> are in this preſent ſmall volume compriſed, compact together by the induſtrious and pleaſaunt Artifice of the firſte Authour, vnder an angry Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and Hiſtoricall narration of the Grammer warre, of this pleaſaunt and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured
<pb facs="tcp:27750:9"/>
hiſtorie, no leſſe profitable than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable. <hi>Lucian</hi> an eloquent Greke Auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor made the firſt draughtes in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle of the Alphabet letters: but this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath waded further euen vnto verbes and Nounes, being principall heades of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and to the adherents of ſpeach, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to the congruate worde, (being the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pener and the declaratiue of the ſenſe) as otherwiſe, wherin reſteth al arte and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, wherin alſo all the wiſedome of man is compriſed: ſhaping and fourming theſe two heades, and the auxiliate ayding par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with ſuch fayned perſonages and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie properties ſo apt and to them ſo quicke in qualitie, that hee giueth life, bodie, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon and armour to deade wordes, yea, and ſounding voyce, to ſubſtances inanimate and without ſoule: ſo that the Reader in the lecture of this (though fayned) narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and dreadfull diſcouerie, ſhall deeme them no more to be vocall wordes, but by a ſtrong iudgement shall thinke them dap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlye diſguiſed, being tranſfourmed into liuelie perſone, going, ſpeaking, and ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſoning with continuall terrors of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
<pb facs="tcp:27750:10"/>
expedicion and exploites, with alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goricall conflictes of bloudie battaile, not onelie in hoſtile contention abroade, but alſo in ciuile, yea, and inteſtine Warres at home: ſo that in the diſcouerie hereof he is nothing obliuious of anye thing that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth to the deduction and ſafe gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſo great affaires, euen from the firſt cauſes and entermixed medlies of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures, vnto the laſt ende of all their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes and endeuors, with all their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, all their tumults and vproares, with their doubtfulneſſe of victory among manie martialiſtes, how of bloudie battaile diuers loſſe and daungers doe followe, and how in the ende finall peace enſueth. All which matters be ſo properlie penned, and ſo cunningly compact in this tragedie, that the warres of the Peloponnenſes, and the ciuile warres of the Affricanes in Thucide, in Saluſt, &amp; Lucan, are peraduenture more high and diffuſedlye deſcribed: But with more arte or more compendiouſlye, I am ſure they are not. So that it is ſothly to be ſaide, that our Author through the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of his learned wiſedome, doth as the
<pb facs="tcp:27750:10"/>
good Geometricians doe, which the inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible greatneſſe of the heauens &amp; the earth do reduce in a ſimple circuit, deſcribing the ſame in a ſmall ſphere or manuel compaſſe. So hee hath placed the mightie, huge, and fearefull factes of armes vnder the figure of ſo ſmall a thing as of the congruitie or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordaunce of words in oracion, ioyning let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with weapons, teaching the arte mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taire with the arte litteraire, ſo well, and ſo exactlye, that the reader beſide the delyght and pleaſure that he shall haue in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſo pleaſaunt an Allegorie, shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue further benefite: for herein is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in one conteipt two vnderſtandings knit togither, the one proper and naturall, the other tropique and figured. Beſide this, he shall comprehende in this ſame ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſubſtance and by the onely labor of one reading, thoſe two ſo worthy things aboue remembred, that doe eterniſe the fame of their fellowes, that is louers of learning, and prudent martialiſtes. The ſcience litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raire, and militaire, that is to ſay, the arte of Grammer, yea the graundmother of al arts and ſciences, and the arte militaire of dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:27750:11"/>
warres, vnder pleaſaunt Metaphoricall figures, tranſported and tourned, berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the minde of the litterall vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſmall things verball, to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of greater, more royall and reall, doth manifeſtly shewe by example the ambici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mouings, the imperiate deſire of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to haue gouernment, the tumultes and parcialities of peoples, the profitable and peruerſe counſaile of ſundrye counſailers, the ſeemely ſentences, and modeſt meſſages of the artificiall erraundes on both partes, their enterpriſed attemptes &amp; martiall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the ſomoning of ſouldiers, the chartes of defiaunce, the denouncing of Heraldes, the high and ſtatelie ſtomackes of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe parties readie to ioyne Battaile, the ſeeking of alliaunce in extremitie, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact confederated of cuntrimen, the flights, treaſons, eſpies, embushements their ſodain entrappes and skirmishes, the ordinaunces of armes, the placing of the campe, the pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of their arrayes, the noble chering of the captaines to their ſouldiers, the taking of tovvnes, the marching of their men, the cruell conflicts and worthy feates of armes
<pb facs="tcp:27750:11"/>
on all ſides, the lamentable loſſe of Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, the cruel combat of the fighters, the great ſlaughter on both partes, the fearefull flying on all ſides, the doubtfull meetinges of many, the indifferencie of their victory, and the finall pernitious accidents that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue through the wars to both ſides, the rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, the reauing, the rapme and diſorder that is then in vre, the depopuling of inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitate cuntries, the deſolate deſtruction that diuers are damnified by the commodities and aduantages that one realme enioyeth throughe the detriment of an other: and contrarily the infinite vtilities that enſue, thorowe peace and concorde, to all realmes and reipublikes. All which things are by wonderfull cunning, and pleaſaunt fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, by moſt exquiſite rule and perfect methode, treated ſummarily in this booke, firſt written in his owne and pure Latine tongue, and after (for the pleaſure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite that therein may be gathered) was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into our english tongue, through the commaundement of a learned perſonage, one who is no leſſe a louer of learning, than vertuous in condition, who for the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:27750:12"/>
of his example is to be followed as a meete patrone of humaine curteſie.</p>
            <p>Wherefore (gentle reader) when thou art delighted with the profitable lecture of this hiſtoricall diſcourſe, attribute the thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy good wil to be the cauſer of this english tranſlation, wherin albeit that there be not the ſame ſweeteneſſe in our phraſe that it hath in his owne tongue, yet I doubt not but it shall ſeeme that I digreſſe but ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilie from mine Aucthor: For as the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned knowe, it is an abſurde and harde mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in this treatiſe properlie to english the greateſt part of thoſe words that touch the argument in apt phraſe correſpondent to the Latin, ſithens the ſame coulde not bee done by a learned tranſlator into the french, which tongue doeth nearer appropriate it than ours: Therefore whereas of ſome I may be thought little to alter in tranſlation from the latine Aucthor, therein may the Reader iudge me to followe the Frenche phraſe who is my patrone partly in moſt of my tranſlation, and when I shall ſeme in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie point to digreſſe from the french tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator, I doe it the nearer to followe the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:27750:12"/>
Aucthor, ſo that the Reader I hope wyll iudge indifferently of my doings. VVher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in my tranſlation I thought it requiſit (yea, and alſo no leſſe neceſſarie) to leaue the moſt parte of the wordes of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their owne tongue, eſpeciallye for that this diſcourſe of the Grammer warre was made vpon the Grammer of the latine tongue firſt, and not of the french. VVhat will it then auayle (will ſome ſaye) to haue tranſlated it into english? whereto in the firſt place it may thus be aunſwered, that for that it was the free good wil of the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator, that in hys labour on this behalfe thought not to offend, neither to do wrong or diſpleaſure to any, but that through hys meane the ſimple and vnlearned englishe readers, aſwell as the learned latiniſts, might enioy part of the pleaſure that is had in the lecture of this delectable diſcourſe of this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured warre, and bloudleſſe battaile, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mortall shot, ſweate or Cannon poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And furthermore that his meaning was, for the vtilitie of our english children beginning to ſtudie the latine tongue, who reading this pleaſaunt fight in their ovvne
<pb facs="tcp:27750:13"/>
tong (as the French in theirs) might learne by waye of mirth and merrie paſtime, the principal pointes of the Romayne Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: Finally the ſame might ſerue for an exempler aſwell hiſtoricall for the inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and guide of martiall affaires, as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, therin to conſider the harmes that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue thorowe the diſſention of Princes and great Lords, parents, kinſmen or neighbors, how the communalties of realmes and cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries can not eaſelye profite in anye wealth and aboundance, without trafike and quiet paſſages one to another, and howe diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion procureth diuerſe dangerous damma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to them and theirs: Shewing alſo on the other ſide the ſingular benefites that peace procureth, what commodities are enioyed by the vniformitie of kings &amp; Princes raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in one regiment or country louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly togither in one faith, lawe, and tongue, friendly as one: which things (as I ſuppoſe) are the principall cauſes whye this booke was firſt compiled by mine aucthor, which by chaunce happening into my handes, and by me ouer redde, to my ſingular delight in both tongues, determined with my ſelfe to
<pb facs="tcp:27750:13"/>
participate parte of my vnderſtanding to the youth of my nation, thorowe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of a friende, who might haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded me. VVherefore if I eſpie the friendlie receipt hereof, in no leſſe grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full parte, than it was friendly fauoured of ſome, I shall be the readier encouraged to bid thee hereafter to ſome better banquet, in the meane whyle let the courteous rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vſe a friendly gueſtes parte, not miſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any thing that is ſet freely before him. And albeit that this my tranſlation be not ſo exquiſitly englished on my parte as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny better learned can doe, yet in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my painefull good will, I doubt not your friendly receipt of the ſame. And thoughe that the french tongue (whereout I extracted this worke) in adages and breef termes haue an eaſier concluſion of ſpeach than our engliſh tongue, yet let the Reader be aſſured what ſoeuer termes be altered (if any be) the matter is perfite, pleaſaunt and profitable to the reader, and much matter contayned in this ſmall Booke, both of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and delicate lyking, ſuch as the gentle reader maye gather great fruite, wiſedome,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:14"/>
and worthineſſe by, if hee applie his dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence therevnto. And for my parte I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed my labours in this behalfe, not to winne fame or fauour, but to beſtowe my leyſures well and to fruitfull exerciſe, to the benefit of my countrey men, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corage thoſe that can doe better to the like exerciſe. And if any vnfit wordes happen to be eſpied of better and more eloquent heades, yet I truſt that ſuch will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne a good worke, for an ill wrighter, neyther a good worde for an ill ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. What or howe effectuall matter is contayned in this Booke, in the ſequele is manifeſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:27750:14"/>
            <head>¶<hi>The diſcourſe of the Grammer warre:</hi> betweene two Kings, the <hi>Noune,</hi> and the <hi>Verbe,</hi> contending for the chiefe place in Oration, wherin thou ſhalt ſée the <hi>Verbe</hi> to preuayle.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is none ſo ſimple in iudgement, that doubteth the ſoyle of the Grammer to be the faireſt &amp; happieſt of all the renoumed parts &amp; prouinces of the world, aſwell for the pleaſantneſſe of the place wherein it is ſituate, being in good and holſeſome ayre, and aboundaunt in all fruites and other good things, withoute which this mortall lyfe may not eaſilye be paſſed: As alſo for that ſhée hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes and euer, béene the Nourſe and bringer vp of all people of renoune. For euen as in this age, euen ſo long tyme heretofore, the cuſtome and maner euer was in all landes and countries (except among the rude and barbarous nacions)
<pb facs="tcp:27750:15"/>
where anye were eſpied of prone and readie nature, bent towarde forwarde wit, they were ſent thither to be taught and inſtructed, and perfitly to learne the moſt holy and learned ſciences: For by this onely way and paſſage is the entrie and acceſſe to the higheſt countries, and noble houſes, as <hi>Dialectice</hi> (that is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorike) <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> that is learned wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; <hi>Theologie,</hi> that is the moſt high and excellent knowledge in diuinitie. In ſo much that vnleſſe they enter tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the Prouince of <hi>Grammer,</hi> no ſoule were able to attaine to the worthy ſecreats of the other prouinces. And albeit that the ſame Regions abounde in all pleaſure, yet not withſtanding, it is ſo enuironed about with high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and ſuch ſharpe rockes, right dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficile and harde to be got vp vppon, that hardlye without a good guide, any maye euer attaine to the plaine and pleaſant path of them. And therfore bicauſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde ſhoulde not be reſtrayned from ſo neceſſarie a benefite, the good and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cuſtome euer was, and yet reaſteth
<pb facs="tcp:27750:15"/>
to the kings of the ſaide lande, to ſende abrode through euery part of the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall worlde, ſome of their expert knights and worthy Capitaines of olde bandes, properly called <hi>Pedagoges</hi> &amp; Schole ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that they might ayde others, and ſurelye conducte them of tender age to the princelye pallaces of the ſaide kings, (as for the mightie, and ſuche as nowe drawe towarde age, hardely ſuffer to bée taught of anye,) to the ende that the youth there being taught in the ſciences of the Gréeke and Latine <hi>Minerue,</hi> might the eaſlier and more lightly aſcende and go ouer the foreſaide countries. There haue all learned Grekes and Latins made their apprentiſhode, who by their worthy writings, or by the act of others, are immortaliſed with renoumed fame. Being there thus well taught and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they haue afterwarde ſo floriſhing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye liued through the high praiſe of their illuſtrious and ſplendant actes, that they liuing, were vnto all men in their time great ſetters forth of vertuous exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and after they were deade (yet as
<pb facs="tcp:27750:16"/>
aliue) ſhewed to thoſe that ſuruiued the as it were by poynting with their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the right path and readie way to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned honorable life, &amp; immortall fame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>But although that this lande of <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> be none other but indeuidate and withoute partialitie, yet neuertheleſſe there are two mightie kings, that there raigne and gouerne, that is to wéete, the <hi>Verbe</hi> and the <hi>Noune.</hi> The <hi>Verbe</hi> hath to name <hi>Amo,</hi> and the <hi>Noune <hi>Poeta.</hi>
               </hi> Who a verye long time raigned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſuch concord and quietneſſe, that to fourme Oration perfect, wherin the beautie of them both (the higheſt place of the one, and the chiefeſt ſeate of the other) dependeth no diſſention, diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or contencion was euer hearde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene them: For in all their territorie there grew nothing more eſtemed, more worthie, or more ſounde, than Oration, which being beautified with the moſt coulors of ſundrye flowers, and decked with the moſt faire and fine figures, and with the moſt ſwéete &amp; perfumed Buds of ſet Roſes, was of ſuch ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:27750:16"/>
and aucthoritie, that ſhe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye drewe vnto her all mankinde (when the ſame is right and aptly applied) but may alſo withdrawe any of the Goddes which waye ſhe will winde them. By reaſon whereof <hi>Euripides</hi> ſayth. That which force coulde not gayne, that faire ſpeache did ſoone attaine: <hi>Pirrhus</hi> alſo vſed ſometime to ſaye, that <hi>Cyneas</hi> dyd winne more townes with his tongue and comelie ſpeache, than he with hys warres. Theſe two kings then being in ſuch concorde, as all the affaires of <hi>Grammer</hi> were in good apparence and better eſtate, it happened that for a ſmal thing diſſention ſprang betwéene them, whereby vpon a verye ſodaine, all was bewrapped in vprore and martiall dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſures: For what harme is that that wine &amp; inſaciate eating cauſe not? That and ſo great amitie and vnion betwéene theſe two Princes was ſo ouerthrowne at one onely banquet, wherin they were both droncken: and ebrietie ſet them in ſo great ennimities one againſt another, that eyther of them, pricked forwarde
<pb facs="tcp:27750:17"/>
with ambitious deſire of regiment (as wilde Buls ſlong of gadde flies) almoſt vtterly euer turned their own realmes, and the noble empire of <hi>Grammer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But nowe let vs ſhewe howe their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate happened, to the ende that euerye one may knowe, that there is no bande or knot of amitie ſo ſtrong, that deſire of ſuperioritie may not breake. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the olde <hi>Dennis</hi> vſed not cauſeleſſe to ſaye, that euen he that hath the Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe in his lap, hath cauſe himſelfe to feare, and to beware of friendes: ſeing that it is certaine, that euery man loueth rather to be ſerued, than to ſerue other.</p>
            <p>As theſe two Kinges on a time were at a banquet, in the middeſt of the hoate Summer, neare to a pleaſaunt &amp; cleare ſpring, hauing the water bancke on the one ſide, and the other moſt pleaſant and ſingulerly ſhadowed with the braunches of gréene Willowes &amp; high Plane trées, after they had ſufficiently banquetted, warmed with wine, and lightned wyth drincking, a queſtion aroſe betwene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to weete, whether of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two were grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb facs="tcp:27750:17"/>
in aucthoritie &amp; of moſt importance to performe Oration? Then the <hi>Verbe</hi> minding to holde the worthieſt place, was ſharpelye withſtoode of the <hi>Noune,</hi> affirming, that without him, Oration and ſpeach might not be, &amp; that through him altogither, the ſame is vnderſtoode and of better grace. And what doſt thou (ſaide he) without me in Oration? if I withholde me a parte neuer ſo litle, the hearers vnderſtande thée no more than one that were dombe &amp; ſpake not. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther awhile a ſmall part of ſpeach wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me, and do that the hearers may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande that which thou ſpeakeſt. Doubtleſſe if I be not there for an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter, none maye ſo much as geſſe the leaſt thing of thy meaning, More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer thou ſhouldeſt note, that in ſo much as I am elder than thou, ſo much more am I approoued worthieſt. Who is he that knoweth not the <hi>Noune,</hi> before the <hi>Verbe</hi>: Or who is he that is ignoraunt, how the beginning of the <hi>Noune</hi> is more auncient than the <hi>Verbe</hi>? It is infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that God made all things, who if hée
<pb facs="tcp:27750:18"/>
made all, made alſo the <hi>Verbe.</hi> Nowe God is a <hi>Noune</hi> and not a <hi>Verbe</hi>: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nowe of conſequence, by the <hi>Noune</hi> were all things made, yea, Oration it ſelf was made of God, and ſo the <hi>Noune.</hi> As for thée, O thou <hi>Verbe</hi> (that arte ſo proude) thou haſt thy calling of me: haſt thou neuer red, that among the Sonnes of Women, is not a greater than <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi>? this is Gods ſentence, it is not lawfull to go againſt it. Wherefore if none be greater than <hi>Iohn,</hi> for that it is writen that his name is <hi>Iohn,</hi> and agayn that his name was <hi>Iohn,</hi> it is apparaunt to be ſeene, that there is not, neyther may any thing elſe, be greater than the <hi>Noune.</hi> I coulde alleage to this matter ſixe hundreth places, whereby it is proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued clearer than the day, that as in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe and antiquitie, euen ſo in aut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie &amp; chiefe place the <hi>Noune</hi> is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the <hi>Verbe.</hi> Al which things I ſette and leaue a part, to the ende that men thinke me not to precede the <hi>Verbe</hi> more thorow much babling, than of iuſt cauſe. O <hi>Poeta</hi> (aunſwered the <hi>Verbe</hi>)
<pb facs="tcp:27750:18"/>
I maruayled before nowe, why that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine <hi>Plato</hi> had expulſed thée out of hys common Weale: But nowe knowing how ſhameleſſe and light thou art, ſo to intermixe the holy ſcripture among thy follies: I know well that the learned &amp; wiſe <hi>Plato</hi> iudged rightlye of thée. For had not he exiled thée with manye other, forth of the reipublike that he ordayned, thou haddeſt by thy falſe ceremonies, fearefull Goddes, and other things cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the ciuile maners of his citizens. For what pernicious thing durſt not thy great pride &amp; arrogance, enterpriſe and attempt? Yea ſeing that by thy deuiſed deceiptes, and falſe writhed witneſſes, thorowe force writhed from holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, thou laboreſt to caſt me down fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dignitie of the chiefeſt place, which I haue long time in this lande poſſeſſed.</p>
            <p>But certainly, for that it ſhall not ſéeme to thée, that thou alone arte learned, I will eaſlye alleage more manifeſt and plaine teſtimonies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame holye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that maintaine mine aucthoritie, I wil ſet here for moſt the very beginning
<pb facs="tcp:27750:19"/>
of that euangelicall Scripture, where it is thus ſaide. In the beginning was the worde, and the worde was with GOD, and God was the worde. Open thyne eares nowe, wherefore hideſt thou thy face ſo? God (ſaide he) was the worde, and moreouer, all things are made by him: And withoute him nothing was made. It is not therfore the <hi>Noune</hi> then that made all things, but the <hi>Verbe.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, god was a <hi>Verbe</hi> and not a <hi>Noune.</hi> Moreouer, by the Worde the Heauens were made firme and ſure, and all their powers.</p>
            <p>What wilt thou now ſay? There is no meane to defend thée by holy allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maiſt perceiue them to make for me, and not for thée. But let vs bend to thoſe poyntes that aptlieſt tende to our cauſe: Tell me I praye thée, whence commeth to thée this folly and madneſſe? And whence haſt thou ſo ſodainly taken ſuch ſtomacke and heart of grace, that thou dareſt vſurpe vpon thée the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt place in Oration? Knoweſt thou not that all comelineſſe, beautie and ſwéet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:27750:19"/>
commeth of me alone? and that the <hi>Noune</hi> is alwayes ruled of the <hi>Verbe,</hi> &amp; not that the <hi>Verbe</hi> is ruled of the <hi>Noune.</hi> The comelye featneſſe of the <hi>Verbe</hi> is that, that beautifieth and enricheth O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: and if I gouerne thee not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, thou ſhalt be halfe handed and of no force. Knoweſt thou howe to make a conſtruction, wherin forthwith the chief place is not giuen me? Beholde all men knowe, that I onely that holde the ſeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niorie ouer the <hi>Verbes,</hi> can without the aide of any other make perfect Oration. Wherefore then ſpeakeſt thou ſo imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentlye? And (as <hi>Horace</hi> ſayeth) why throweſt thou ſo thy proude and diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſixe cornered words? who art thou? what art thou? of what force? or howe great? not of ſuch aucthoritie as thou boaſteſt of I am ſure, that ſo goeſt puffed and ſwollen, that it is maruell thou bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſt not in the middeſt. I am (thou wilt ſay) the King of the <hi>Nounes.</hi> But what is thy name? thou wilt aunſwere <hi>Poeta.</hi> And what is <hi>Poeta</hi> other then a pratler, a ſeller of gaudes, a deuiſer of fables, a
<pb facs="tcp:27750:20"/>
maiſter of miſchiefe, a brabler, a Lyer, a dronckerd, &amp; a fooliſh dolte, that coloreth that which is truth, and putteth forth fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoode, and ſuch a one as by thy pratling, filleſt and perturbeſt all the worlde. Which alſo by thy chat vſurpeſt ſo much aucthoritie among the common and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſort, that thou dareſt ſtriue for the dignitie againſt the renoumed ſtocke of the <hi>Verbes.</hi> Foliſhly do thoſe fathers that giue thée their children to be taught of: for what is in thée whereby the youth maye be encited to grace and vertuous encorageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but the Stewes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous <hi>Iupiter,</hi> the ieloſie of <hi>Iuno,</hi> and the Whoordom of <hi>Venus,</hi> and of the Ruffian <hi>Mars,</hi> and ſuch goodlye deuiſes imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of thine owne brayne, that hauing droncke a little more than well, thou, as filled with a deuine ghoſt, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laden with wine, madlike or diueliſhly, dareſt mixe heauen with earth, &amp; earth with heauen.</p>
            <p>At theſe wordes <hi>Poeta</hi> the King, all fiered in Ire, not able to ſuffer the ſhame nor the iniurie that was ſayde of hym,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:20"/>
aunſwered thus: O thou moſt miſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous heade of man, dareſt thou ſpeake ſo boldely ſuch contentious things of vs? And there withall caught a Cuppe in his hande, which had violentlye hit hym on the face, had not one of the ſtanders by, (holding him by the arme) tourned the ſtroke a part. It is not to be doubted now, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rage wherein both partes were then, but that wordes were no blowes: but certaine of the elder ſorte and wiſeſt came vpon the ſame, and they bare away the ſayde kings all droncken into their Pallaces: and on the morrow after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the friendes of the parties were aſſembled, there was great enquirie and diſputation of the contention happened the day before. Then of the parte of the <hi>Nounes</hi> was ſharpelye blamed, the open throate &amp; vnbeſéeming talke of the king of <hi>Verbes,</hi> &amp; the moſt part of the <hi>Nounes,</hi> eſpecially the yonger of them, maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly muttered, ſaying that the tongue of King <hi>Amo</hi> ought to be tamed, and to giue him to vnderſtande, that the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie maieſtie of the <hi>Nounes</hi> was neuer
<pb facs="tcp:27750:21"/>
ſubiect to ſuch reproch and contumely.</p>
            <p>But although the Elders that were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there preſent, eſpecially <hi>Terence,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed them that nothing might bée vnaduiſedly done, but that it was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite rather firſt to take counſaile than weapon in that point, following the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſorte: yet not withſtanding, all the <hi>Nounes</hi> with their King, were ſo fleſhed to fight, that it was forthwith fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined and accorded to offer battaile to the <hi>Verbes:</hi> And therevpon was ſent forth a Trumpet to the King <hi>Amo,</hi> aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly to denounce and indict open warre againſt him. On the <hi>Verbes</hi> parte was no wiſer counſailes helde, for when all their nobilitie were come togither, ther was nothing elſe treated of among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than to defend the dignitie of the <hi>Verbes</hi> in the lande of <hi>Grammer,</hi> and to depreſſe &amp; throwe downe the pride of the <hi>Nounes.</hi> And behold, herevpon came the Harolde of the King <hi>Poeta,</hi> who diligentlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the charge of his errande. They aunſwered, that with good will they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued the defiaunce, and from thence
<pb facs="tcp:27750:21"/>
forwarde all their mindes were bent wholy towarde martiall affaires. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde the King of <hi>Verbes</hi> ſent trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets and meſſengers to all nations and landes that were vnder his ſeigniorie, commaunding that all ſuch as were able to beare weapon, ſhoulde be founde rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in good order at the day aſſigned.</p>
            <p>Firſt before all other came <hi>Quando</hi> the Duke of <hi>Aduerbes,</hi> with ſixe of hys Capitaines, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Quo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde Qua Quor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum</hi> and <hi>Quouſque. Quorſum</hi> and <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque</hi> were companied with their bands, and vnder the firſt Enſigne were theſe renoumed Champions. <hi>Hic Illic Iſthic Intus Fores Ibi Ibidem Sicubi Alicubi Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Alibi Vſque</hi> and <hi>Nuſquam.</hi> Vnder the ſeconde, <hi>Huc Illuc Iſtuc Intro Foras Alio Nequo Aliquo Siquo Illo Eo</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odem.</hi> Vnder the thirde, <hi>Hac Illac Iſtac Alia Nequa Illa</hi> and <hi>Eadem.</hi> Vnder the fourth, <hi>Horſum Illorſum Iſtorſum Intror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Extrorſum Dextrorſum Siniſtrorſum Aliorſum Aliquorſum</hi> and <hi>Deorſum.</hi> Vnder the fift, <hi>Hactenus, Hucuſque, Eouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquemodo</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque nunc.</hi> To the
<pb facs="tcp:27750:22"/>
ſixt bande the Capitaine himſelfe bare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Enſigne, marching in the middeſt of his men, ſo that two of the ſaide bands were in the forewarde, and the other three at the taile.</p>
            <p>Many other <hi>Aduerbes</hi> ſerued for fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners, and theſe diſcouered the wayes and ſerued for Partiſans, the reſt coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the wings and kept that the bandes marched not out of aray. The names of them are <hi>Peregre Pone Super Supra Inter Infra Extra Citra</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltra,</hi> with many other. After them came other <hi>Aduerbes</hi> great of quality, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tity &amp; nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, among whom were thoſe hideous ſwering <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes:</hi> as <hi>Aedipol Enimuero Ecaſtor Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuſſidius</hi> &amp; <hi>Profecto.</hi> Alſo the calling <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes</hi> as <hi>Heus &amp;c.</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> anſwerers as <hi>Hem.</hi> The laughers as, <hi>Ha Ha He.</hi> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying <hi>Aduerbes, <hi>Minime</hi>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>Nequaquam:</hi> which <hi>Nequaquam,</hi> albeit he were vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt &amp; greatly trayned vp in the wars, was yet notwithſtanding the moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true and deceiptfulleſt of them all, and woulde neuer ſay truth but thorow con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraynt: The Gréekes called him <hi>Holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:27750:22"/>
which is as much as altogither a denier, or deceitfull interpreter: Many mo things could I report of this Ruffler <hi>Nequaquam,</hi> that moſt daungerous and hurtfull beaſt, but bicauſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes at theſe dayes are not in common terme I willingly ceaſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beleuing doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that it is loſt labour to warne the Shepe how he ought to kéepe him out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wolfes daunger. Now theſe <hi>Aduerbes</hi> were armed with thrée kinde of armure, for they had kynde for a buckler, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for an headpiece, and figure for a ſword. Many other <hi>Aduerbes</hi> came to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayde of their King as Indicatiues, Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatiues, Meditatiues, Diminutiues &amp; Denominatiues, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their bands, which were not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempned. The mighty lord of <hi>Nounes</hi> animales (being <hi>Nounes</hi> out of rule, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beare great ſway and lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe in the borders of <hi>Grammer</hi>) were not laſt and hindmoſt: doubtleſſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men of Warre, but yet not able to holde their araye: they are called, <hi>Sum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olo Fero</hi> and <hi>Edo.</hi> By reaſon whereof it was permitted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pitch their tents
<pb facs="tcp:27750:23"/>
in anye part of the Campe where they woulde, leaſt they might raiſe vprore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſouldiers. The nation of the <hi>Verbes</hi> defectiues came alſo thither very braue, and in goodly order, <hi>Memini, Noui, Cepi</hi> and <hi>Odi:</hi> Alſo <hi>Vale Salue Aio In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit Faxo Cedo,</hi> being all armed poynt deuice readie to ioyne battaile. After them folowed all the <hi>Verbes</hi> actiues, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in bone and brauery, with alſo the Neuters, with the Deponents, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons &amp; <hi>Imperſonals:</hi> Al of them of ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry fourms and ſtraunge languages, &amp; were armed with Genders Tenſes Moodes Kindes Perſons and Numbers.</p>
            <p>The King <hi>Amo</hi> after he had thus aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled his hoſt, pitched his campe in the wide playnes of Coniunctions, in a place called <hi>Copula,</hi> &amp; encamped his hoſt there, neare to the hoſt of Diſiunctiues called <hi>Sine:</hi> And deuided his Hoaſt into foure coniugations, giuing to euerye of them a meete place (except to certayne familiar <hi>Verbes</hi> who were encharged to beare the Baggage of the Infinitiues: Their names are, <hi>Incipit, Deſinit, Debet,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:23"/>
Vult, Poteſt, Iubet, Audet, Nititur, Tentat</hi> and <hi>Dignatur,</hi> with ſuch lyke: this office was aſſigned them, for that they were willing therto, and had ſturdie ſtrength and abilitie. Laſt of all came certayne <hi>Verbes</hi> extract from high place, and of great dignitie, <hi>as Pluit Ningit Fulgurat Tonat Fulminat</hi> &amp; <hi>Aducſperaſcit:</hi> brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with them certayne bands of their moſt worthy Champions: But the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundes with the Supines, forſaking the <hi>Nounes,</hi> came and yelded to the <hi>Verbes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Poeta</hi> King of <hi>Nounes</hi> heard y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great preparation of his aduerſarie, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be ſurpriſed with ſome ſodayne alarum, if he abode the furie and force of his enimies without purueyaunce to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende him, commaunded all the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of his Realme, that in the ſpedieſt maner they might, they ſhoulde make themſelues readie to be in the fielde ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſo aptly equipped, as in beſt wiſe were poſſible for them. Then to the aide of the king of <hi>Nounes,</hi> firſt came the Dukes of the <hi>Pronounes,</hi> as the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt kinſemen, who for the moſt parte
<pb facs="tcp:27750:24"/>
were often times Princes <hi>Ego, Tu, Tui,</hi> being of the Bloode royall, &amp; of the ſtock of the <hi>Arſacides,</hi> with whome were, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Tuus Suus Noſter</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ester, Noſtras</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſtras, Ille Ipſe Iſte Hic</hi> and <hi>Haec.</hi> Al the <hi>Pronounes</hi> were parted in manye fourmes, and vnder ſundry Enſignes. Some were Primatiues, other Deriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, ſome poſſeſſiues, and ſome gentils. After them came the right worthy Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, who had a long time haunted the warres, of which the firſt was <hi>Hic Haec Hoc:</hi> The ſeconde <hi>Hic et Haec:</hi> the third <hi>Hic et hac et hoc,</hi> armed with Genders, Numbers, Figures, Perſones, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. After them came the graunde Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaynes of Interrogatiues, Infinitiues, &amp; Relatiues, <hi>Quia qui que quod vel quid:</hi> and theſe ioyned to the hoſt. Theſe were the generall referenders of all the land of the king of <hi>Nounes,</hi> with whome were all the Relatiues and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, deuided into two bandes: that is to wéete, in Idenditie, and diuerſitie. In the firſt were, <hi>Is Suus Ipſe Ille Idem.</hi> In the ſeconde, <hi>Caeter Alius Reliquus</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:27750:24"/>
The Prince of the accidentall rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues was <hi>Qualis,</hi> vnder whome fought <hi>Quantus quot quotuplex quatenus quotenus quotiſuriam cuias</hi> &amp; <hi>cuigena.</hi> The Quéene of the Prepoſitions called <hi>Ad,</hi> came thither alſo with <hi>Ab</hi> &amp; <hi>In,</hi> the huſbandes of <hi>Nounes</hi> Caſuals, &amp; they brought with them thrée Enſignes of worthy <hi>Amazo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> Vnder the firſt were <hi>A ab abs cum coram clam de ê ex pro prae palam ſine abſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que tenus,</hi> which ſerued to the Ablatiue Caſes. Vnder the ſeconde were <hi>Ad apud ante aduerſum aduerſus cis citra cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum circa contra erga extra inter intra infra iuxta ob pone per propter prope ſecundum poſt trans vltra praeter ſupra circiter vſque ſecus penes,</hi> all ſeruing to the accuſatiue caſes: But <hi>In ſub ſupra</hi> and <hi>ſubter</hi> ſerued to both caſes, to wéete, to the Ablatiues, aſwell as to the Accuſatiues. Vnder the third were, <hi>Di dis re ſe an con,</hi> whoſe office was to puruey potatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſouldiers, for it was then Lent. Who albeit they were by compoſition inſeparable, leaſt they ſhould at any time be voyde of that was enioyned them, were yet ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:25"/>
that ſundrye times they claue to the <hi>Nounes,</hi> &amp; ſome while to the <hi>Verbes:</hi> and therefore they were accompted the common roges of the campe.</p>
            <p>Nowe the <hi>Nounes</hi> thus deuided by bandes, marched in goodlye aray, that is to wéete, the Subſtantiues, likewiſe the Adiectiues, <hi>Nounes</hi> proper, appellatiues, and participles: After whome were the braue and rich comparatiues, ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, poſſeſſiues, patronymiques, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils, (which were noble) numerals, and multiplying, which gouerned the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde borders. Euery of them were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided by fiue declinations, to wéete, by the firſt, the ſeconde, the thirde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth and fift, and they were all armed wyth kindes, genders, number, figures and caſes. All the ſayde bandes reduced in one, <hi>Poeta</hi> the King of the <hi>Nounes,</hi> caried his hoſt into the ſame playne of coniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and pitched his campe on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of the ſaide riuer <hi>Sine:</hi> So that betwéene both the hoſtes was nothing but the Riuer: By reaſon whereof, ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye times there happened ſharpe ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:25"/>
betwéene thoſe that went there to the water, notwithſtanding yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out open battaile, for that had both the Kings forbidden, bicauſe all nedefull ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries for the warres, were not yet very readie.</p>
            <p>Nowe eyther of theſe Kings coueted to induce to his parte the Participle: a man doubtleſſe of very great aucthoritie through all the lande of <hi>Grammer,</hi> yea, in puiſſance and dignitie, altogither next &amp; neareſt the King: who without doubt was able alſo to cauſe victorie to whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide he woulde winde him. By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this, aſwell the <hi>Verbe</hi> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Noune,</hi> left nothing vnaſſayed, eyther of them hoping to haue him on their ſide. <hi>Poeta</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of <hi>Nounes</hi> putting forth formoſt, wrote to him in this maner. I doubt not (O my brother) but that thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt with what pride and puffed ſtomacke <hi>Amo</hi> the King of the <hi>Verbes</hi> is riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mée, and againſt the dignitie of <hi>Nounes,</hi> and by what lawe I minde to occupie the chiefeſt ſeates to conſtrue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: For which thing, ſeing that the
<pb facs="tcp:27750:26"/>
ſame doth ſo much moue and diſpleaſe me, I am forced to take armes and ſet ſouldiers in the fielde, that his pride be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beaten doune, we maye keepe oure ſeigniorie in his right, vncorrupted. And ſithens thou knoweſt howe much thou art bounden to the nation of the <hi>Nouns,</hi> and what great benefit thou haſt recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of vs, as genders and caſes, numbers and figures: Thou ſhalt therefore doe a worke worthy of thy faithfulneſſe and friendſhip, if with thy men of warre and thy ſouldiers, thou come to ioyne with vs to defende our common Titles, our common ritches, and common hope. For if the dignitie and lordſhip of <hi>Nounes</hi> be deſtroyed, thinke not thou to finde anie ſure place in all the lande of <hi>Grammer,</hi> and ſo fare well: Beſeching thée to ſet forward thy coming in the ſpedieſt wiſe thou mayeſt.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, <hi>Amo</hi> the King of <hi>Verbes</hi> wrote to the ſaide Participle in this wiſe. I know very well (O deare brother) howe thou art by our enimies verye inſtantly ſolicited to be on their
<pb facs="tcp:27750:26"/>
part, to warre againſt vs: And albeit that we haue hope, that by thy ſingular wiſedome thou wilt not doe any thing ſo raſh or vnaduiſedly, yet neuertheleſſe it ſemeth good vnto vs, to admoniſh and aduertiſe thée, that thou conſider in thy ſelfe, what commodities thou haſt recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of vs, and what increaſe of dignitie the <hi>Verbes</hi> haue made thée, in making thée partaker of their Tenſes and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, Numbers and figures. And if thou haſt any ſmal benefit of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Nouns,</hi> thoſe that thou receiueſt of vs are much more, yea and alſo greater. Thou ſhalt therefore doe beſt if thou repaire to our happie folde, not alone to keepe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende vs, and the lordſhip of the <hi>Verbes,</hi> but alſo thou thy ſelfe, and thine. For thus thinke with thy ſelfe, that if I haue the worſt, mine enimies will not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde them from running vpon thy lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe and turne their victorious armes (which God forbid) againſt thée: that they all alone may with their mad will runne in and ſpoyle al the land of <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> Farewell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27750:27"/>The Participle after that he had red y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde letters of the two kings, thought nowe of the one, then of the other, and had ſundry thoughtes in his heade, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering with him ſelfe that he coulde holde part with neyther of them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great and euident loſſe of his owne goodes. Contrarily if he ſhoulde ſéeme to miniſter, he might not onely enioye the fauor of them both, but alſo that he ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſhed, to ſee them low brought tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the hazard of the warres, that they being deſtroyed, he might afterwarde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone withoute reſiſtaunce, poſſeſſe the ſayde lande of <hi>Grammer:</hi> and therefore thought good to diſſemble, féeding them with faire wordes, vntill he knewe who ſhoulde haue the better, therfore he wrot to them in this maner. I haue moſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant kings, receyued your letters, and I haue red them with great ſorowe and trouble of minde, knowing that betwen two ſuch princes ſo knit, is fallen ſuch diſcorde, that you can not withholde you from ouerthrowing thorow cruell war, your owne lordſhips, and that renoumed
<pb facs="tcp:27750:27"/>
empire. But wherewith are ye vexed? or what harme holdeth you? and whence commeth this madneſſe? I beſeche you for god his ſake conſider a little whither you go. Howe will our common eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (thoſe beaſty citizens of ignorance, and that ſlouenlike people of <hi>Barbarie</hi>) reioyce, vnderſtanding the ſtrength of their enimies to be ſo waſted through their owne contentious quarelling? I adiure by the high Gods aboue and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, that ye withholde you, &amp; forbeare ſuch deadly, mortall, and abhominable battayles, leaſt that through a damnable deſire of ſuperioritie, you bewray in vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rores and ſlanders the goodlieſt prouince of all the worlde. But if deſtinie will haue it ſo, and that you be ſo fully purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to debate your quarell by the ſword, I purpoſe to take part with neyther of you, ſeing my lordſhip dependeth in part of the <hi>Verbe</hi> and in parte of the <hi>Noune.</hi> And for that I am greatly bound to you both, with what I can I will ayde you both with vitayles, munitions, and other neceſſarie things: But as touching facts
<pb facs="tcp:27750:28"/>
of armes, I will withholde me, &amp; I wyll cauſe my Souldiers to be aſſembled in armes, to kepe in at home, that through incourſes no iniurie be done by any, on the frountiers of mine owne lande: I pray God giue you better cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayle. Fare ye well.</p>
            <p>And albeit that he had thus written to them, this ſubtill and wily for neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, through all poſſible meanes hée might, maintayned the quarell, and by his priuie letters incited the mindes of both nations egerly to ytche againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hoping thereby (as I haue ſaid) that he ſhoulde eaſily attayne to the ſeignio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the whole <hi>Grammer</hi> after their to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall deſtruction. Then hauing aſſigned a day for his ſubiectes to be aſſembled in, was in a moſt trim and braue companie. Firſt the Terminat in <hi>Ans ens dus rus tus ſus xus,</hi> were there with the <hi>Nounes</hi> verball in <hi>Tor trix</hi> and ſuch like, which were neighbors of the <hi>Verbes</hi> &amp; <hi>Nounes,</hi> and ioyned with the Participles. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Gerundes and Supines, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde theſe ciuil wars, withdrew them
<pb facs="tcp:27750:28"/>
alſo from the <hi>Verbes,</hi> and fled to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiples. Theſe things thus appoynted, the Participle ſent great giftes to both ſides, to be alwayes and ſtill in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and firſt he ſent to the <hi>Verbe</hi> theſe vnder named neuter paſſiues. To wéete <hi>Gaudeo ſoleo audeo ſio prandeo Coeno iuro ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tubo placeo nubo careo moereo poto taceo</hi> and <hi>quieſco.</hi> To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King of <hi>Nouns</hi> he gaue the ending in <hi>Tor</hi> and <hi>trix.</hi> He ſent alſo for wagis to the hoſt of <hi>Verbes</hi> an hundreth waggons of preter Tenſes, of Preſent and future tenſes. Item a thouſand Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels laden with figures, ſimples, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites, and decompoſites: And to the <hi>Noune</hi> he ſent by the riuer <hi>Siue,</hi> Tenne ſhips laden with nominatiue and geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue caſes, with as manye ſinguler and plurall numbers, and a great number of other, maſculine genders, feminines, neuters comons and all. This done, he helde him in his country with his men of warre, awayting to whether ſide for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune woulde tourne hir. In the meane while, theſe two warlike kings hauing verye well made prouiſion of all things
<pb facs="tcp:27750:29"/>
neceſſary to giue battaile, awayted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe than ſome trimme occaſion to commence the warre. But it chaunced that two of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthieſt townes of <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> (to wéete) <hi>A</hi> and <hi>V</hi> were taken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed by the king of <hi>Verbes,</hi> albeit that then all townes were indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubiect, &amp; payed equall tribute to both the ſayde kings, aſmuch to the one, as to the other, being moreouer in nothing more in ſeruice to the one King, than to the other.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Poeta</hi> the king hearde this, he toke by the like policy thrée other touns <hi>EIO:</hi> The other hearing this, kept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their ſtrongeſt watch, &amp; keping their liberty, wer comon to both parts, whoſe names are, <hi>BCDFGLMNPQRS TXZ,</hi> and of them doubtleſſe commeth all the force of <hi>Grammer.</hi> To eyther of the Kings were giuen two dipthongs to be their trumpets, for they were taught by ſounde of trump, to moue the ſpirite of all the ſouldiers for to fight. <hi>Ae</hi> and <hi>oe</hi> ſerued to the King of <hi>Nounes, <hi>Au</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>eu</hi> to the <hi>Verbes.</hi> Beſide this, certayne ieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:27750:29"/>
or gibing women folowed both the hoſtes, that moued the mindes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in ſundry affections: for ſome wept and bewayled the ſlaughter that ſhoulde be among them of <hi>Grammer,</hi> yea &amp; that they felt the ſame néere them alreadie, as <hi>Oh ah he heu</hi> and <hi>hei,</hi> other were dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, and reproued the contention of theſe kings, as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ah vae</hi> and <hi>atat.</hi> Other woundered of ſuch diſſention fallen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene ſo great friendes, as <hi>Papae vahu</hi> &amp; <hi>vha:</hi> other as fooles incited and encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſouldiers to fight, as <hi>Eia</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uax.</hi> Moreouer, all the men of warre and ſouldiers being well appoynted and readie to enter into the battaile, it ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med good to the king of <hi>Verbes</hi> that on his part gladly withall his hart he would withdrawe to commence ciuile warres, and to cloke his doing in or with ſome honeſt maner, wrote a letter to the king of <hi>Nounes,</hi> in this tenor. O <hi>Poeta</hi> thou haſt well vnderſtoode in what appoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and readie ſtrength I am come downe to ſhewe my ſelfe in the fielde to giue thée battaile: &amp; agayne thou mayſt
<pb facs="tcp:27750:30"/>
knowe that there are not in thée ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent forces able to abide and withſtande the violent ruſhing in of the legions of my men of warre: Therefore thou ſhalt doe wiſely, if in leauing me in my eſtate thou withdrawe into thy territories. But if thou be ſo ſenſeleſſe, that it muſt be had by the edge of the ſworde, then know thou that thrée dayes hence I will be readie with mine hoſt in the playne fielde to fight, there to receiue thee. When the Trumpets <hi>Au</hi> and <hi>Eu</hi> had giuen their letters to the king of <hi>Nouns,</hi> he aunſwered them according to his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile in this wiſe. O <hi>Amo,</hi> thou euer haſt to many wordes, but it is not nowe a time to amaſe the eares of the hearers with thy much babbling: thou boaſteſt thy valiaunt hoſt, and thy fearefull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared ordinaunce, as if on our ſide wée had not but dwarfes and Graſhoppers. Thy poſſeſſion hath euer bene very lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in Oration: But yet thy follye lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thée thither from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thou mayſt not flie, vntill with that parte of lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (by thée wrongfully woon, worſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:30"/>
and naughtely retayned) thou be by iuſt warre chaſed out. And for that thou ſhalt knowe how litle, not I onely, but mine, doe way thée, and how ſmally we feare thy threatnings, our Heraldes <hi>Ae</hi> and <hi>oe</hi> ſhal ſhewe thee their bare but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tockes if thou wilt: farewell, ſuch as I wiſh thée: adewe to the Deuill for euer and aye.</p>
            <p>By theſe letters the heartes of them poyſoned one againſt another, did all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayte with fierie ſtomackes the laſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned day of battayle. In the meane while, by occaſion of ſuche troubleous time, there aroſe (as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly doth in ſuch buſineſſe) a licence of moſt miſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous déedes, and there went forth a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of priuy pilferers through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole prouince of <hi>Grammer,</hi> ſeking their pray, and eſpecially in wooddie places, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hils eſpied the paſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, and ſpoyled the vittailers that went to the Campes: Whereby great dearth and ſcarſitie of victuales daylye encreaſed in both the hoſtes. By reaſon wherof, certaine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie capitaines, with ſufficient number
<pb facs="tcp:27750:31"/>
of ſouldiers were by the conſent &amp; decrée of both kings ſent out to flea theſe robbers or elſe to driue them far out of the lands of <hi>Grammer.</hi> They being come thither, the ſouldiers did encloſe a very thick wood, where they hadde vnderſtoode that there were a great number hidden: ſo they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet them, that one eſcaped not vntaken. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whome was a certayne fellowe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Catholicon</hi> that draue a great Aſſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with Gréeke and latine words bound vp togither, and caried them into Italie. Item an olde <hi>Duns</hi> called <hi>Hugution,</hi> with a yong yonker ſurnamed <hi>Garlandia</hi> which alſo with a great one eyed Mule draue a waggon laden with falſe and broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rules, and fowle fourmes not onely of olde phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but alſo of latine termes, wherewyth he hoped to be enritched in the borroughes &amp; townes, ſelling them as precious things ſet in glaſſe, to make laten of glaſſe which might haue day ſéene through it. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer this yoncker of <hi>Garlandia</hi> was found ſtuffed full of falſe peces of money &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfait coyne, being baſe bullion, which he cauſed to be taken for good, being of an
<pb facs="tcp:27750:31"/>
vntrue ſtampe which he had forged, and of the ſayde money he had filled all the lande of <hi>Grammer.</hi> Lykewiſe there was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a great and greaſie laſie lourden, that made himſelfe be called <hi>Greciſmus,</hi> that had made leane all the victayls that went to the campe, to ſtuffe a greate foule ranck ſtincking and rotten calues paunch with. There was alſo taken one <hi>Pylades,</hi> that had robbed all the wayes he went in, and was become ritche. All theſe were there bodily puniſhed as they had merited, ſome quartered and made in pieces, ſome brent in the fire, other caſt into the dongeons of perpetuall and ſtincking priſons. He that toke and puniſhed <hi>Greciſmus</hi> was a right worthy Capitaine called <hi>Touſſan</hi> or <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan.</hi> The robberies of <hi>Pylades</hi> was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered and debarred by a noble capitaine very well acquainted in the warres, which was called <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Cuuella</hi> that ſo ſwelled that he was in perill to be dropſie, but one gaue him a ſhort cliſter, that did yelde him in ſlender fourme, &amp; more leaue and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be borne than he was. All the reſt of this robberous rable were deſtroyed, ſlaine
<pb facs="tcp:27750:32"/>
and buried in a great and darke dungeon. <hi>Catholicon</hi> that among them was called the great, was brought to the campe wyth his Aſſe, who confeſſed on the racke (albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it it were a thing manifeſt) that he had ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len all theſe wordes in the lande of <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> Then when he was aſked ought in Gréeke, he aunſwered that he vnderſtode not the Greke, and of the Latine but a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little. Then ſayde the Iudges, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore carieſt thou wyth thée Gréeke words, ſeing thou then vnderſtandeſt not? Then he aunſwered, there is ſo great ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce of learning with vs (ſaith hée) that albeit I ſpeake groſſely, yet can I ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily make them beleue that I am through lined in euery corner with all the eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>Attica.</hi> All they which were there, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this, fel in a great laughter, and ſaid: by ſaint George, ſeing that thou haſt ſuch hearers as thou haſt, that which we know not the due owners of, thou ſhalte carrye with ſaulfconducte to thy people and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but that which we ſhall know to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to any, that we thinke good to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to the due owners. Then after they hadde made diligent ſearch, all the Gréeke
<pb facs="tcp:27750:32"/>
words almoſt were giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Iſydore,</hi> whoſe they were, and the remnaunt to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines: to which buſineſſe was appoynted the mayſter of the trenchmen, called <hi>Cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin</hi> with the courteous capitaine <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> of <hi>Nebriſſe.</hi> The intermixed, rotten, and ſecret hidden words were giuen him, and ſo they permitted him to go his way with his Aſſe lighter laden than before: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe they forbad him at any tyme euer after, to be ſo hardie as to call hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Gramarian, except among the rude and barbarous people. In theſe buſie bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, one <hi>Priſcian</hi> a very renoumed man, and of great honour in the lande of <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> for that he coulde not ſuffer the ſaide lande to runne in totall ruine through ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile warre and contention, haſted toward the campe in poſt to make an agréement, and being taken, was ſpoiled and ſore bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the feloniſh felowſhip of <hi>Catholicon</hi> &amp; was ſo wounded on the heade, that there was no ſalue able to heale him. Shortly after, among theſe felowes was taken one who falſely and ſhamefully ſayde that he was an hiſtoriographer, and had gathered
<pb facs="tcp:27750:33"/>
togither a great bundell of Ieſting ſoliſhe gaudes in a great volume, called <hi>Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Chronicharum,</hi> who forced tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe queſtion, confeſſed that all they were ſtollen things: and ſo he was exiled for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer into the lande of ignoraunce. As theſe things were doing, certaine of the <hi>Verbes</hi> anomales, as <hi>Sum volo fero,</hi> with thrée com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of their handmaides, made an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault and toke away a priſoner of the capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the <hi>Nounes</hi> named <hi>Caeter,</hi> which was of the race of Relatiues, and they toke him hidden with his fellowes in an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh, in what caue I knowe not, neare to the by path way of the coniunctions <hi>Quod</hi> and <hi>Quam,</hi> and him they ſlue with all hys ſingulers, his plurals ſeing the daunger they were in, made a vowe to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> to ſacrifice him the remnant of their goods, &amp; ſo they eſcaped hole and ſounde miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly. When tidings hereof were told to King <hi>Poeta,</hi> he was maruellouſly moued, and it greatlye greeued him to loſe ſuch a Capitayne: for this <hi>Caeter</hi> was very ſtout and ful of ſtomacke euen to the vttermoſt, and in feates of warre he had no péere.
<pb facs="tcp:27750:33"/>
The king of <hi>Nounes</hi> therfore féeling him ſelf greatly endomaged with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> &amp; his ſingulars, diligently awayted oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion whereby he might render double the lyke to his enimies. But fortune, who can in all thinges do very muche, and chiefly in warre, gaue hym ſhortly after the way to reuenge him of the wronge. For in thoſe dayes many legions of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes</hi> of no ſmall authoritie were taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners by certayne lyght horſmen of the <hi>Nounes.</hi> Among who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was <hi>dice, face, fere</hi> and <hi>duce,</hi> of the bande of the imperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and commaunders. From whom thorough great ignomie was cutte away by the kings commaundement, the hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſkirtes of their garments, ſo that they ſhewed their buttockes, and ſo ſent them away againe, ſo that euer ſince they were called only <hi>dic, duc, fac</hi> and <hi>fer.</hi> Afterward he commaunded that the priſoners ſhould be ſlayne, namely, <hi>fuo, ſpecio, leo</hi> and <hi>pleo:</hi> whoſe goodes were by the king of <hi>Verbes</hi> giuen to their lawful children, diſcending of them in right line, as <hi>fui, fuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fuiſſem, fuiſſe</hi> and <hi>futurus.</hi> And to the children of
<pb facs="tcp:27750:34"/>
               <hi>ſpecio,</hi> who were a great number, as <hi>aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio conſpicio</hi> and ſuch like: and alſo to them of <hi>leo</hi> &amp; <hi>pleo,</hi> as <hi>doleo impleo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pleo ſuppleo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleo expleo oppleo.</hi> At the very ſame ſeaſon was bewraied a great treaſon to the hoaſt of the <hi>Verbes,</hi> how certaine horribe hoore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the ſtocke of preterperfectes, being ſouldiers, to cloake their treaſon, and not to be knowen, were diſguiſed after the maner of the <hi>Greekes,</hi> though they were of the <hi>Latin</hi> tong, and beyng taken, had two heades. Theſe had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpired and layd watch for the king of <hi>Verbes:</hi> but beyng taken and conuict of the fact, were decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red traytours, and condemned of treſpaſſe againſt the king, they were called <hi>momor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di cecidi cucurri pepe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di ſpopondi pepigi didi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tetuli cecini peperi tutudi pepuli fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felli memini pupugi</hi> and <hi>tetigi,</hi> from whom was cutte of one head at that preſent: ſo that wheras they were before time called, <hi>momordeo cecido cucurro,</hi> they be nowe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>mordeo cedo curro,</hi> and ſo of the reſt. From <hi>tetuli</hi> were cutte of both heades, as well of the preter, as of the preſent tenſe: albeit that <hi>Terence</hi> through pitie thought
<pb facs="tcp:27750:34"/>
to ſimon on the ſame agayne of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tenſe with Baulme, but it helde not. Now as the time of fighting drew neare, the ſayd kings ſet vp in the hygheſt place of their hoſt, a red cloake, to aduertiſe the ſouldiers that they ſhoulde ſhortly ioyne together in fight, that they might prepare and propoſe them ſelues thereto, takyng their repaſt, and whetting their weapons, might ſharpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their munitions ready, with all other thinges pertaynyng to ſuche af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. In the morning, after the ſouldiers had dined, on both ſids without anynoyſe makyng, the whole hoaſt aſſembled to the ſayde place. Then when they had all raunged in battayle aray with diſplayed aucientes, the ſaid kings beſought and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired their ſouldiers earneſtly to behaue them ſelues wel &amp; worthily: but it was no néede, ſeyng that they of them ſelues were already fired ynough. For al as mad men ſhooke their pikes with ſo great &amp; ſtout a ſtomacke, that they taried for nothing but to ſtrike, &amp; awayted nought but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of the onſet &amp; alarme: &amp; hervpon, behold, the trumpettes blewe the onſet on both ſides.
<pb facs="tcp:27750:35"/>
On the other part the earth reſounded and rang againe, &amp; in both hoaſtes were made great ſhoutes and cries, the heades or both hoſtes made great vowes to God, and euery of them ſtomacked and chéered vp their ſouldiers. Then euery one dyd what he coulde and knewe to be done, they ſtrake together with great han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſtrokes of ſwordes, brake their pikes, that the ayre rang againe of the cry of the fighters. In the ayre was nothyng ſéene but cloudes of ſmoke and brymſtone: on both ſides were great ſtore wounded and of dead corpſes ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty. O there was a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſight to ſée the <hi>Verbes</hi> defectiues (amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the reſt (fighting againſt the <hi>Nounes</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teroclites. Theſe <hi>Nounes</hi> accompanied with their nominatiue caſes, with their genders, alſo with their genitiues &amp; plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall numbers, dyd fiercely lay vpon their enemies. The <hi>Verbes</hi> defectiues did ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and couragiouſly withſtande and put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part theſe <hi>Nounes</hi> Heteroclites, with their indicatiues, accompanied with their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perfect tenſes, ſo that by their coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations they brake thorowe force, the
<pb facs="tcp:27750:35"/>
numbres and genders of the other.</p>
            <p>Of theſe <hi>Verbes</hi> there was one called <hi>aio,</hi> who vſing ſingular hardineſſe, did for a long ſpace reſiſt two <hi>Nounes</hi> Heterocli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſo long that in the end being no more able to withſtande their furiouſe forces, loſt diuerſe of his perſons, modes, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and numbres, and then reſted only vnto hym, <hi>ais, ait, aiunt, aiebam, aiebas, aie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat</hi> and <hi>aiebant:</hi> the reſt paſſed thorough the ſworde.</p>
            <p>As the hoaſtes were thus in fight there was ſuch a mixture, that one knewe not an other, and they were al ſo fiered and fleſhed to fight, that none of them al once perceyued the feareful earthquake y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was at that preſent, and in the ſame countrey there: yea ſuch a one, and ſo great, that it deſtroyed the townes nere therto, turned the ſtreames of mightie riuers the other way vpſide downe, and thruſt the ſea into the floudes, and with his hideouſe roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ouerthrewe the hygh mountaynes with a mighty fall. But let ſuche be ſtyll, that accompt that for a tale: the accident that happened in that ſame ſharpe &amp; harde
<pb facs="tcp:27750:36"/>
warre, wher the <hi>Romayns</hi> were ſo troun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the <hi>Penoys,</hi> neare vnto the lake <hi>Traſimene,</hi> the citie of <hi>Croton</hi> yeldeth ſufficient teſtimonie, whiche (as <hi>Lucan</hi> ſaith in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke of true narratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſituate on the brynks of the ſhore of <hi>Traſimene,</hi> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very preſent, thorough a tempeſt of a whirle wind was tranſported into the mountayne, where it is at this day. Doubtleſſe of this &amp; ſuch like exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples lately befallen, <hi>Titus Liuius</hi> may wel glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in, for that he hath ſo great a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to haue ſayd truth: for that it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to confirme the thinges that he hath writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The ayre was obſcured and made darke with the arrowes that the numbers ſingulars and plurals ſhot. The ſhot of the figurs compoſite and decompoſite flew whiſtelyng ſo rounde &amp; rightely into the eares of euery one, that they were all as deafe. A great number were hurt by the dartes of the kindes of primatiues, and deriuatiues. The trumpettes lykewyſe that went on euery ſide ſounded a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and terrible <hi>Taratantara,</hi> ſo that the ſounde thereof encouraged the fighters
<pb facs="tcp:27750:36"/>
maruellous ful of ſtomacke and hardy, to beare the blowes and ſturdie ſtrypes of their enemies. And theſe troublous ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling women, the interiections that went about the arayes, vexed and ſore trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them all, through their moued and fickle affections: Among whom for the moſt part ware often hearde theſe pitiful and dolorous cries, <hi>heu</hi> and <hi>hei oh ah eh.</hi> Notwithſtanding this warre was more fierce and cruel than long in fighting, and had it not bene for great aboundaunce of rayne, that thorough a ſodayne ſtorme and tempeſt which fell from the cloudes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at that preſent, made the medley to depart and breake off. Then doubtleſſe had there bene an ende of al the forces of <hi>Grammer.</hi> Such and ſo great was the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious rage that they had euery one of them, one againſt another, yea vntill that pointe, that albeit the trumpettes ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the retraict on both ſides, and they all greatly encombred with the water, might neuertheleſſe be vnmingled and ſeparate aſunder one from another, to returne them vnder their enſignes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27750:37"/>The victorie aboade doubtfull and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne, neyther was it knowen of any, whether had the better or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſe, for on both ſides there was a maruellous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as well of ſore wounded as of ſlayne, not only of commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſouldiours, but alſo of the hie and chiefe captaynes. It is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any to tell the great loſſes that were theron both ſides. Notwithſtanding I will aſſay to ſhewe playne and many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly, and in the openlieſt maner I may, that which ſome did winne or loſe there, (though I can not ſay of euery one in particular) this will I do, to this end, that they that come after, may therto take héede. Firſt the parte of the <hi>Verbes</hi> defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, in fight loſt all them that were deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent from him, all his genders, tenſes, modes, perſons and numbers that were of the fourth coniugation, of figure compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, and of the ſingular number. He hym ſelfe (as God woulde) eſcaped ſafe, for ſeyng hym ſelfe in perill, he made a vow, that of no coniugatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mariage, he wold after any more beare the liuery: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was at that brunt ſo ſore feared,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:37"/>
that ſince he hath bene very ſeldome ſéene publikely in the land of Grammer. <hi>Fore</hi> was bereft &amp; robbed of al his goods, except <hi>fores foret</hi> &amp; <hi>fore,</hi> which are of the optatiue mode, of the third coniugation, <hi>vale, aue, ſalue,</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kindred &amp; ſtocke of the impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues (loſt a great many of their fellows) whiche are yet lyuing, the reſt were loſt. <hi>Faxo</hi> of the ſame ſtocke of actiues eſcaped only with thrée of his, al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of his band after him were ſlayne, except <hi>faxis faxit</hi> &amp; <hi>faxint,</hi> who ſaued them ſelues with him by flighty footing. <hi>Inquio</hi> of the ſtocke of the neuters, kept <hi>inquis inquit inquiunt inquam inquies inquiet inquient inque</hi> and <hi>inquam.</hi> The reſt periſhed in the warres. <hi>Inquiens</hi> at that time was with the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples wherof he happened well. <hi>Apage</hi> and <hi>apagite</hi> when they had loſt all their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, eſcaped alone. <hi>Diet</hi> loſt alſo all his fellowes except <hi>dieſcit. Facio</hi> was put from his ſonne <hi>facior,</hi> who notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng before he dyed, dyd conſtitute by knightly teſtament an heire <hi>fio. Poſco diſco metuo timeo renuo reſpuo compeſco vrgeo lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo,</hi> and all they of the race of the actiues,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:38"/>
loſt their ſupins. Some <hi>Verbes</hi> loſt their preter tenſes of the thirde coniugation, and in place of them, they after recouered the pretertenſes of the fourth coniugatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: among whom was, <hi>cupio peto quaero arceſſo faceſſo</hi> and <hi>ſero.</hi> Some <hi>Verbes</hi> hauing loſt their future in <hi>am,</hi> to the ende that they woulde not thencefoorth wholy loſe the hope that was to come, bought other fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at the faires of <hi>racana,</hi> as <hi>eo queo</hi> and <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neo</hi> (but <hi>Horace</hi> by his auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie gaue to <hi>lenio lenibo,</hi>) al <hi>Verbes</hi> belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to beautie loſt all their ſupins, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g whom was <hi>lucco fulgeo ſplendeo polleo</hi> and ſuch like. <hi>Fulcio</hi> vſing a ſingular hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe eſcaped out of peril, &amp; held his <hi>fultum,</hi> but ſeyng we haue recounted &amp; told of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that receyued loſſe, it is not mete to holde of no accompt theſe <hi>Verbes,</hi> that behauing them ſelues wel &amp; worthily had both ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and dignities, whiche they receyued of their king, beſide theſe others that they firſt had &amp; enioyed: among other were ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate &amp; ſet vp in great honor, <hi>caeno iuro ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reo ma reo nubo</hi> and <hi>pra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deo:</hi> for beſide their owne preter tenſes, they receyued alſo the
<pb facs="tcp:27750:38"/>
preter tenſes of the paſſiue voice. <hi>Redimo</hi> was enriched in his fiue ſenſes of nature, &amp; at that preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t obteyned foure ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as to deliuer, to leade &amp; gouerne, to decke and ornate, &amp; to take to ferme. <hi>Solor</hi> wan thrée ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as to be alone, and to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort &amp; exhort, <hi>explicat,</hi> beſide his own ſenſe which is to explicate and ſhew foorth playnly, receyued, that he might declare, ſhew, that he might drawe, that he might repreſent &amp; deliuer. <hi>Valeo</hi> beſide his owne ſenſe, which is to be in health and whole, wan ſo much, that when he ſayd <hi>vale,</hi> that he might ſalute alſo, &amp; ſometime curſe too. <hi>Preſto</hi> had foure ſignifications as, to lend, &amp; to be aloft, to do good, and hold promiſſe, with diuers other ſignifications. <hi>Haurio</hi> was as much enritched, for he had foure ſignifications, as to draw out, to wounde, to heare &amp; ſée and diuerſe other ſuch lyke, and all they when néede is are reduced in one. <hi>Paſco</hi> receyued two vnderſtandinges, to féede, and bring vp. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aco</hi> albeit he med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not much among the fighters (for as <hi>Socia</hi> ſayth in <hi>Plautus,</hi> the fiercer they fought the faſter he fledde) neuertheleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:27750:39"/>
fortune that oftentymes giueth rewarde to the ſlouthfull, woulde enriche his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardiſe with the beſt of the ſpoiles: for as he eſpied certaine of his enimies that wer fled and gone away, he crept out of his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin and cloked them in his fiſt: who after bought them againe with a great ſumme of ſiluer, and he wan beſide his owne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſenſe ſeuen other, to wete, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, to leaue of, to ſerue, to be ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluouſe, to be lawfull, not to haue, and to be empty. <hi>Studeo</hi> wan thrée ſignifications, as to ſollicite, to deſire earneſtly, and to be very paynfully buſied. <hi>Pango</hi> receyued thrée ſenſes, as to ſing, and hath giuen to <hi>panxi</hi> in his pretertenſe to make truces, and hath gyuen to <hi>pepigi</hi> to faſten &amp; ioyne together. <hi>Sapio</hi> from that day had two ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to wete, to giue knowledge, and to be wiſe. <hi>Fero</hi> one of the foure anomales gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thrée ſenſes, as to vphold, to deſire, and to beare. <hi>Confiteor</hi> had thrée ſenſes, to praiſe, to purge, and to make manifeſt. <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pero</hi> receyued ſeauen ſenſes by reaſon of the great aucthoritie that he had among the <hi>Verbes</hi>: as to remayne in part, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:39"/>
to be neare, to go further, to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, to ouerliue and excéede. Some <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes</hi> there were, whiche hauyng loſt their owne preter tenſes, had of their king the goodes of other <hi>Verbes</hi> paſſiues whiche were ſlayne at the battayle: as <hi>audeo fido gaudeo ſoleo</hi> and <hi>fio.</hi> Theſe peſtiferous and perillous lying <hi>Verbes,</hi> whiche alwayes haue in their heart and minde other than in the mouth, albeit they had no parte of the praie, ye tought not they and their names to be left in obliuion, but ſpoken of, to the ende that euery one might know them, and ſo beware: ſeyng that alwayes vnder the colour &amp; cloake of doing, they beare the paſſiue voyce: they are called <hi>exulo veneo nubo liceo</hi> and <hi>vapulo.</hi> This laſt of all is the moſt wily and ſubtilleſt: and therfore ſo muche wyſer as the boy is, ſo muche the more héede wyll he haue to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline his wily ambuſhes, yf he haue good care to kepe his buttocks. Now ſeyng we haue already ſhewed as well as we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that which happened to the <hi>Verbes,</hi> it ſemeth good in our acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt that we ſpeake alſo of the <hi>Nounes.</hi> Ouerſight was made
<pb facs="tcp:27750:40"/>
in and thorowe the hoaſt of the <hi>Nounes,</hi> and it was found howe fortune had bene as muche diuerſe to one parte as to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And to the end that we begin by the poſitiues, there was certaine of them, that beyng hurt in their comparatiues, recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued dreſſing &amp; cure through the dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of certayne expert phiſitians, as <hi>melior minor dexterior <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſterior plus magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tior,</hi> &amp; <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tior</hi> al irregulate, &amp; deſcending of the ſecond declenſion. But <hi>pius arduus egregius tenus</hi> and ſuch lyke, loſt their owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiues. The <hi>Nounes</hi> ending in <hi>er,</hi> loſt <hi>ruus,</hi> in their ſuperlatiues: &amp; for the ſame they had <hi>rimus,</hi> as <hi>tener,</hi> and <hi>ſaluber.</hi> To o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for that they had loſt <hi>ſimus</hi> was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>limus,</hi> as <hi>humilis facilis gracilis ſimilis agilis,</hi> and to <hi>vetus</hi> was geuen <hi>veterrimus.</hi> Among trées were certayne <hi>Nounes,</hi> that quiting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues manfully, by a ſodayne miracle chaunged altogether at once their kinds, beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of females, males, euery one aſtonied at the ſodayne caſe, demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded whence came ſuche tranſformation to them: of them were <hi>rubus</hi> and <hi>oleaſter,</hi> which <hi>Titus</hi> ſayth were euyll and vnluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie
<pb facs="tcp:27750:40"/>
tokens, and therfore affirmed he that they ought to be caſt into the bottome of the ſea, or elſe to be exiled out of the lande of <hi>Grammer.</hi> But the king <hi>Poeta</hi> ieſtyng at the fende ſuperſtition that they had in the miracles, dyd prohibite all and euery of them, to harme, or any way to hurt them: ſaying that it was not an euyl ſigne, or vnhappy accident to be chaunged from women into men: ſayng that out of anoughty and croked kind, they were tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a good and better. From certaine <hi>Nounes</hi> heteroclites, fighting againſt the <hi>Verbes</hi> defectiues, were cutte away both coddes and cullion in the plurall numbre (from whiche peryll God ſaue vs) ſo that afterwarde there was in that number founde neither man nor woman but chaſt neuters: whiche doubtleſſe is a thyng greatly to be pitied. Their names were <hi>ſibilus auernus infernus menalus ſupparus baltheus tartarus dindimus,</hi> other had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter chaunce: for when in the ſame number they were neuters, wer glad forth with to ſée them become males: as <hi>porrum raſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>num</hi> and <hi>coelum,</hi> But theſe ſayde <hi>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:27750:41"/>
and <hi>raſtrum,</hi> as they went thorowe <hi>Rome,</hi> founde in the markets of <hi>Agona</hi> their neuter plurals, &amp; there they bought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe with a great ſumme of money, and gyuing leaue to the mules, loued bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to hold them to them there. <hi>Balſamum</hi> among all <hi>Nounes</hi> and trées above only a neuter: by reaſon wherof ſeyng that he coulde not beget nor bring foorth yong, is in ſo great ſcarſitie that he is no where ſéene but in the lande of <hi>Iuda,</hi> which is the cauſe (as ſorowefull) he yeldeth his fruict all in teares: as for other <hi>Nounes</hi> that were bereft of their plurall neuter, recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the feminine for amendes, as <hi>epulum oſtreum veſper</hi> and <hi>cepe.</hi> But truth is, of all creatures the oyſters only were neuters: but aboue al aucthors <hi>Plinie,</hi> &amp; the poetes holde them for neuters, wherefore <hi>Ouide</hi> ſayeth thus: <hi>Oſtreaque in conchis, tuta fuere ſuis,</hi> ſo that afterwarde they gayned ſo, that they became as muche feminine as neuters: others that were of the doubtfull gendre, receyued the maſculine in their plurall numbre, as <hi>Cardo, bubo,</hi> and ſuche lyke, other that were ſpoyled of all their
<pb facs="tcp:27750:41"/>
caſes plural, abode euer ſince diſmembred and maymed: among whom, were <hi>ſumus limus funus puluis ſanguis mundus pontus ſol ſal</hi> and <hi>vuus,</hi> all of the maſculine gendre. Hardly is ſéene any tyme more than one Sunne in the firmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but when it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth ſo, it is not naturall, but rather wonderful, likewiſe alſo certayne femini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes loſt their plurall caſes, as <hi>lux ſitis la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes mors vita fames tabes gloria fama ſalus pax humus lues tellus ſenecta ſoboles iuuenta indoles proles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe fought ſo febly in the hoaſt,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all their plurals there they loſt.</hi> Other feminines loſt at the ſayd conflicte their ſingular nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, as <hi>argutiae habenaebigae blanditiae cunae delitiae exequiae excubiae exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiae phalerae facetiae genae gades inſidiae indi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae caleridae lachrymae latebrae minae,</hi> &amp; many others. Other neuters were ſpoyled of all their plurals, as <hi>coenum foenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auus ſolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pus and virus.</hi> Furthermore other wer put fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al their ſinguler frends: as <hi>arma caſtra ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta cunabula co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chilia crepundia paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a moenia mapalia magnalia ilia ſeria precordia</hi> and <hi>ſponſalia,</hi> yea and almoſt all the names of
<pb facs="tcp:27750:42"/>
feaſtes, as <hi>Naturnalia Dioniſia Aphrodiſiae B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lia, Floralia</hi> and <hi>Neptunalia,</hi> and all the names of metals, eſpecially <hi>aurum &amp; argentum,</hi> which euery one laboured to take priſoner, and likewiſe <hi>aes ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta</hi> &amp; <hi>aera</hi> in three caſes. In lyke maner for the great heate and alteration of the combat, the meaſures were ſpoyled of the pluralitie of their liquors, except of wines, and honies, which to the plurall caſes were ſpared, to the ende that they myght do kyng <hi>Poeta</hi> ſervice with newe wines: for that he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them well. <hi>Oleum</hi> and <hi>frum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tum,</hi> by like miſfortune were ſo gluttonnous, that thorowe the great ſcarſitie that was in the hoaſt, they wer not found in pluralitie. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aboad ſhortened in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yltines and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tines plurall, as <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrathura</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>ſera.</hi> Yet neuertheleſſe all <hi>Nounes</hi> had not the worſe part: for diuers of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ſpoyle of their enimies: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herof they were of greater au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> before, ſo that ſome receyued other nominatiue caſes beſide their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tch alſo hath <hi>arbos: honor</hi> which hath <hi>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os: od<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> which hath <hi>odos: cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumer</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:27750:42"/>
which hath <hi>cucumis: cin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which hath <hi>einis,</hi> and <hi>pulue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which hath <hi>puluis.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng they occupy theſe not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, but kepe this ſhare for hie feaſtes, as for trim &amp; nice decking for honor ſake. <hi>Plaga</hi> albeit through hurring he bled, yet wanne he foure other ſenſes without ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the firſt, (that ſignifieth a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, or hurt:) as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he would ſay the arming cord of a net, alſo a great ſpace of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth (called <hi>clima,</hi>) alſo a great kind of linen, ſuch as the old matrones of <hi>Rome</hi> ware when they went in the citie, &amp; alſo for a bed, or any part of a bed, <hi>Opus</hi> the ſame day wan there thrée ſenſes: for <hi>opus</hi> ſignifieth earth: vnder <hi>opus</hi> he giueth ayde, vnder <hi>opibus</hi> riches. The gerundes and ſupins, bicauſe they were ſo often fled to the enimy, were amerced to fine after the treatie of peace was made betweene both the ſayde kings, through the earneſt complainct and ſupplication of <hi>Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> who alleaged the lawes of <hi>Solon,</hi> by which it was commaunded, that ſuch wer to be put a part from all honor and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that in any ſedition had not holde the
<pb facs="tcp:27750:43"/>
part of the one nor the other: for that ſuch a one thinketh altogether of his owne bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>keth not of the common wealth: the greateſt part then in the lande of <hi>Grammer</hi> lyued after the lawes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi> Afterwarde therfore the king of the <hi>Verbes</hi> left to the gerundes no more but only thrée caſes, takyng away from them for the treſpaſſe of their default al their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſes. To the ſupins only were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued but two: whiche greatly greued all them of <hi>Grammer,</hi> ſharpely blaming ſuch a ſort of fooliſh preceptes of <hi>Solons</hi> lawes, as much as the fonde reaſons of <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes,</hi> whom they ieſted at, ſaying, that he had left (his cunnyng at home) his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffs bandes and woull, and that he had not fained ſquint eied diſeaſe in vaine, to haue yerely reuenues and preferment: bycauſe he hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d not to haue ſo much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of the gerundes &amp; ſupins, as he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time had had of <hi>Harpalus.</hi> Surely yf I woulde deſcribe forth all the loſſes &amp; miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tunes orderly as they ought to be, and alſo all the conqueſtes of the worthineſſe of euery one that changed in that day, my
<pb facs="tcp:27750:43"/>
matter would be to long. And therfore I will here make an ende, and this may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, that what ſo euer is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d loſt, waſted, or ioyned to, and growen vp through all the lande of <hi>Grammer,</hi> and his borders and vtter limites, is wholy procéeded tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the ſame harde, hideous, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall fight among them. In the ſame tyme of the warres ſprang vp many new wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and ſundry olde were put apart and reiected. And had not three honeſt perſons ben choſen for arbitrers (of whom we wil ſpeake hereafter) whiche by their power and abilitie withſtoode the naughtineſſe of certayne Grammatiſtes or ſlender gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſo great barbarouſneſſe had then ben mired thorough the <hi>Latin</hi> tong, &amp; the ſame then ben ſo myngled with fooliſhe woordes, that all hope had ben loſt euer to reſtore the ſame againe in his honor, and comely beautie. Therefore after that the retraict was blowen of both the hoaſtes, and that they had numbred as well the wounded as the ſlayne, and had knowne the great loſſe that was of the hoaſtes, they all began and fell to ſighing: and the
<pb facs="tcp:27750:44"/>
ſight of ſuche a ſlaughter of their people greatly greeued them, through deſire of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie. Wherefore euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, ſought nowe nothing elſe than to make peace. And firſt of all <hi>Poeta</hi> ſeyng of <hi>Nounes</hi> after he has called his ſouldiers (but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> without teares) ſayde theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. I thinke well that you knowe (O my Fellowes) how dolefully, and againſt my will, I haue taken araies to defend &amp; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the honor (as euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I thought) and the authoritie of the <hi>Nounes</hi> ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inſt our brethren the ſouldiers of the <hi>Verbes</hi>: and in ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many kindes I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſayed to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and put of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong from betwéene vs the warres, and they to leaue vs ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ct in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. But when I thinke not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> loſſe, but alſo of theirs, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine when I beholde the dead corpſes on both ſides. I haue greater deſire to lament than to ſpeake. Therefore it behoueth vs to remember that, which ſome of our good olde citizens and Burgeſes wrote of the diſcorde and civile warres, as well of the <hi>Romaynes</hi> as the <hi>Grekes,</hi> and howe with great reproches they blame &amp; deteſt the
<pb facs="tcp:27750:44"/>
ambition of them. In good fayth if we had thought of this at the firſt, we neuer had gone to ſo great folly, neither had we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as blinded with anger and rage franti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely and as voyde of reaſon, torne our proper fleſhe ſo with our owne handes as we haue. But (as an other fayth) that which is done and paſt, is eaſier to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued than amended: neuertheleſſe it is better to ſtay thus than to followe on a noughty beginnyng: for yf we wil be ſo mad as to fight with our ſelues thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the ende, doubtleſſe then is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalitie of <hi>Grammer</hi> vtterly come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and then ſhall be gyuen ſo great an ouerture and entrie into the ſame to the Barbarous and ignorant people, that as they will they ſhall rule all: ſeyng none ſhall reſiſt them, and go before to preuent them. By reaſon wherof (O my fellowes) for the comoditie of both realmes I am willingly determined to aske peace with the king of <hi>Verbes,</hi> and of myne own frée will, will go toward him and giue him my hande. Notwithſtanding, thinke not here by that I ſpeake it for that I haue loſt ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:45"/>
or for that I am timorous: but bycauſe there is nothyng more ſure that the affayres of the <hi>Nounes</hi> &amp; <hi>Verbes</hi> can continue, vnleſſe they be friends together knit &amp; quiet in one: of my ſelfe I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mine office, not doubting but that I teache you that, which ſerueth to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite &amp; commoditie of euery one in general, being ready willingly to do what your wil is. God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you aid in al your enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. The profitable oration, &amp; no leſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying of the king, greatly pleaſed all the aſſembly, and all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ſouldiers cried aloude, that that which the king had ſo wyſely ſpoken might be right diligently done. So there was four from the campe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Verbes</hi> for Embaſſadours certayne of the wyſeſt of them: &amp; ſo lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe of the chiefe of the <hi>Nounes</hi>: who hauyng firſt made without much difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie a truce, finally came in ſuch agrement with the king of <hi>Verbes,</hi> and his greateſt lordes, that thrée perſonages ſhoulde be choſen which ſhould be exactly ſéene, and well vnderſtanding in all cuſtomes, rules and termes of <hi>Grammer</hi>: and that at their
<pb facs="tcp:27750:45"/>
award and arbiterment, (after a ſolemne othe ſworne theron) both parties ſhoulde hold them and their reſt without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction. Great was the difficulty, and much more was the diſputation, to whom the charge ſhoulde be gyuen to make the treatie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace. Many procured meanes to haue the ſame office on them, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers was the voyce gyuen, &amp; other againe toke it from them: In the ende it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréed by <hi>Priſcian, Seruius</hi> and <hi>Donalt,</hi> and alſo by al the others co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenting, that thoſe vndernamed, ſhould haue the charge and authoritie to knitte and make ſure the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticies of the peace: that is to wet, <hi>Phedra, Volatteran</hi> chanon of <hi>S. Peters</hi> churche, a man of great eloquence, and better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Item <hi>Peter Marſe</hi> chanon of ſainct <hi>Laurence</hi> in <hi>Damaſcon,</hi> a ryght learned man, and <hi>Raphael Lippe</hi> Florentine, and a great Orator, who beyng ſent for, came to the campe, and hauing there hearde the reaſons on both ſides, &amp; diligently waying the buſineſſe of the matter, in the end pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced this ſentence. To the kinges of <hi>Grammar</hi> to their gentlemen, to their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezens,
<pb facs="tcp:27750:46"/>
and to all ſtudentes to their good happe and comodities be that which now is diſcuſſed. We thrée me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deputed to take away the contencious diſcords, put a part from vs all the ſlaunders, wrongs and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages that heretofore haue come vppon the kinges of <hi>Grammer,</hi> &amp; their ſouldiers, all which we reuoke, take away, and blot out: whiche if they may not be forgotten, at the leaſt our decree is that they be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hereafter more ſpoken of. Item that hencefoorth when a ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to be made, that then both the kinges of <hi>Grammer</hi> in good agrement with their ſubiects come together, as <hi>Verbe, Noune, Pronoune, Participle, Aduerbe, Coniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Prepoſition</hi> &amp; <hi>Interiection.</hi> Item we appointe that in common and familiar ſpeache, the <hi>Noune,</hi> and the <hi>Verbe</hi> only do beare the burden, takyng for their helpe whether of them they will, but to leaue the other by, ſo the ende that beyng put to ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in worke they be not moleſted. Item we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the <hi>Noune</hi> ſerue to the <hi>verbe,</hi> and when he goeth formoſt as touchyng the caſe, ought alſo to be gouerned of the
<pb facs="tcp:27750:46"/>
               <hi>verbe,</hi> but in ſpeach, that the <hi>Noune</hi> be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>verbe,</hi> and the ſame beyng after ought therfore to gouerne the <hi>Noune</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his caſe: but con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erning his perſons &amp; numbres, the <hi>verbe</hi> ought to giue place to the <hi>Noune, Pronoune,</hi> or <hi>Participle.</hi> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we appoint that the <hi>Participle</hi> beare reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>Noune</hi> and the <hi>verbe,</hi> &amp; haue the gouernement of the <hi>verbe</hi> before hym firſt, and that of the <hi>Noune</hi> after him laſt. Furthermore we permit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>verbe</hi> to make oration him ſelfe alone in the ſeconde and thirde perſon, &amp; to put out a part certayne <hi>verbes</hi> of action if néede require, for that he repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted not the <hi>Noune,</hi> but that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented him ſelfe only. This ſentence was gyuen and publiſhed in the preſence of both parties, &amp; it pleaſed very well all the aſſemble, and hath ſince euer bene ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued of all the inhabitantes of <hi>Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer.</hi> Alſo the ſtudie of Italie haue approued it: and in eſpeciall the learned vniuerſitie of <hi>Boloigne</hi> the moſt louing mother of good &amp; forwarde mindes: whiche hath giuen to the court of <hi>Rome</hi> not only ſo many other great perſonages, but alſo euen in this
<pb facs="tcp:27750:47"/>
tyme that ſame ryght learned <hi>Alexander Zambecco,</hi> whiche neuer fletes from the right point, thorowe hope or feare. The vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris</hi> obſeruing the reſt, cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued then for hir ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, that they might pronounce <hi>Nounes</hi> &amp; <hi>Verbes</hi> at theſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and that without any regarde of the qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie of ſillab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es. But bicaſe betwene the relatiues and antecedentes, betwene the adiectiues &amp; the ſubſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ues, betwene the word rege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; the gouerned, betwene the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and determined, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo betwene perfect ſpeache and imperfect was an olde quarel, ſtriuyng whether of them were chiefe and greateſt: it was alſo concluded to ioyne them in vnitie, that the relatiue of ſubstaunce identitale, ſhoulde agrée in gend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, number, and perſon, with his accid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. Item that the adiectiue ſhould obey to his ſubſtantiue in caſe, gendre, &amp; number: and that the gouerned worde ſhoulde followe the nature of the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and that the relatiue of the accident ſhoulde onely repreſent the antecedent in ſuch accident or propertie, in what maner the referred, and the referrent agréed by
<pb facs="tcp:27750:47"/>
rule of diuerſitie with the antecedent: and that the ſpeache imperfect ſhould depende vpon the perfect, &amp; the ſpecified worde, of the ſpecifieng, &amp; betwene two adiectiues, two ſubstantiues, two <hi>verbes</hi> of the infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue mode two perfect ſpeaches, &amp; betwene two imperfects to be no bonde of ſeruice. Furthermore the ſaid <hi>Peter Marſe</hi> would, that betwene ſayings and doinges might be made a peace &amp; agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but the aduiſe of <hi>Phedrus</hi> was, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if that diſcordwer once taken away, the Barbor ſurgions and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne kepers, ſhoulde not haue wheron to be occupied, wherfore they left that thing euen as they founde it. All ſtudentes of ignoraunce, with theſe Baſſards of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary were by commaundement exiled for euer out of all <hi>Grammer.</hi> The Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe were chaſed beyonde the Alpes into their cities and borough townes: but the ignorant thorough the fauour of ſome princes are bred not onely in and through <hi>Italie,</hi> but alſo in <hi>Rome</hi> that mother of good letters: and there whether ſhe will or no, do they continue: among whom there are ſome beyng pourueyed of fat liuings
<pb facs="tcp:27750:48"/>
ſo dull headed and do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tiſh and ſo ignorant in good letters, that if ye aſke them <hi>Amo qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, <hi>partat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> chio vi intenda,</hi> ſo much a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſery they ſurpaſſe in ignoraunce the great mules whereon they are ſo highly got vppe. Moreouer there was giuen irreuoca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le power to the deputed by the ſtrong &amp; ſame counſell of them al to ſearch out, to puniſh, &amp; exile (as things of nature counterfa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored waſtere of <hi>Grammer,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins,</hi> halfe <hi>Grekes,</hi> &amp; they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es that they thought to be preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the honor and aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cement of al <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> letters. And to the end that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the eaſier &amp; more lightly execute their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, were commaunded forthwith to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Romayne</hi> court whereas more filthyneſſe and or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure, and more miſcheuous nough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pranckes are diſplayed, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and honeſt people ſpring on thoſe parts, which power is knowen &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>righthed by great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueledges of Emperors, &amp; learned biſhops, &amp; eſpecialy by <hi>Iulius</hi> that reuerent father, the ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ours of whom God vouchſafe to make his beloued children.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:27750:48"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Henry Binneman, dwelling in Knight Rider ſtreat, at the ſigne of the Marmayde. <hi>Anno. 1569.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
